<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Another extract of more letters sent out of Ireland, informing the condition of the kingdome as it now stands</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 182 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25486</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3258</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19326</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13054982</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13054982</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96993</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25486)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96993)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 406:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Another extract of more letters sent out of Ireland, informing the condition of the kingdome as it now stands</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>62 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ireland --  History --  1625-1649 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:96993:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96993:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>ANOTHER EXTRACT of more LETTERS ſent out of <hi>IRELAND,</hi> Informing the condition of the Kingdome as it now ſtands.</head>
            <div type="letter">
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ithence my laſt to you, that is to ſay, the 23. of <hi>June,</hi> the Marqueſſe went to meete the Rebels at <hi>Caſtle-marten</hi> neare <hi>Killcullen</hi> Bridge, where for the Rebels, there met for the Province of <hi>Leinſter,</hi> the Lord Viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count <hi>Gormonſton,</hi> and Sir <hi>Robert Talbot;</hi> for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>Munſter,</hi> the Lord Viſcount <hi>Muskerry,</hi> and <hi>John Welſh</hi> the Lawyer; for the Province of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naught,</hi> Sir <hi>Lucas Dillon,</hi> and <hi>Ieffery Browne</hi> the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer; for the Province of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter, Tirlogh ô Neale,</hi> Sir <hi>Philem ô Neales</hi> Brother, and <hi>Ever,</hi> M. <hi>Gennys</hi> of <hi>Killwarlin.</hi> There went with the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe, the Earle of <hi>Roſcommon,</hi> the Lord <hi>Moore,</hi> Sir <hi>Francis Willoughby,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Lucas,</hi> Sir <hi>Iames Ware,</hi> Serjeant <hi>Euſtace,</hi> Colonell <hi>Muncke,</hi> Colonell <hi>Gibſon,</hi> and many others; Our Commiſſioners and others were in ſeverall Chambers, and as I heare, Treated by writing, onely ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Meſſengers went betweene them: The Lord <hi>Taaffe</hi> was at that place and very buſie, they continued there till the firſt of <hi>Iuly,</hi> and appointed the 18. of <hi>Iuly</hi> to meete againe, but being better advized upon the unreaſonableneſſe of the Rebels demands, they met no more but brake off the Treaty, as 'tis reported, and are now preparing with all ſpeed to take the Field.</p>
               <p>In my laſt Letters that miſcarried at Sea, I wrote you word of a great overthrow given by Sir <hi>Robert Stewart,</hi> Sir <hi>William Stewart</hi> and Sir <hi>William Coles</hi> Forces, againſt <hi>Owen Roe ô Neale</hi> the Rebels Generall of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lster,</hi> where after a long fight they beate them, and killed 1000. of them as is reported, tooke a very great prey of Cattell, above 6000. Cowes as it is ſaid, many priſoners of note taken, and <hi>Owen Roe ô Neale</hi> eſcaped very narrowly, ſo-that in <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter</hi> appeares no Army of the Rebels, and thoſe <hi>Iriſh</hi> which are left there, are eating up of one another through famine.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:96993:2"/>
               <p>About a weeke before the Treaty for a Ceſſation, here was a report that <hi>Preſton</hi> the Rebels Generall with ſome Souldiers was come into <hi>Meath,</hi> about <hi>Tecrohan</hi> and thoſe parts, but with how many, and for what cauſe, we had not ſo good intelligence as to know yet, Colonell <hi>Muncke</hi> then ready to goe for <hi>England,</hi> was intreated by the State to goe out to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him with a party of men, who yeelded to it; he ſhould have had 1500 Foote at the firſt, and 3 or 400 Horſe, but they were ſo ſcattered here and there, up and downe in the Countrey, that he had but 1200 Foote, and about 150 Horſes, he relieved Caſtle <hi>Iordan,</hi> and ſome other parts thereabouts, and comming homeward by <hi>Clancarry,</hi> about 15 miles from <hi>Dublin, Preſton</hi> meets him with about 6000 Foote, and 600 Horſe, ſome that were preſent there and had ſeene all the Armies on both ſides ſince the Rebellion firſt began, doe affirme, that this of <hi>Preſtons</hi> was the greateſt; both ſides did ſtrive for a ſtraight paſſage which <hi>Muncke</hi> was of neceſſity to goe over, for which they diſputed the matter a good while, but Colonell <hi>Munck</hi> gained it; then they encountred and fought a good while, till <hi>Preston</hi> and his Army very ſtoutly ranne away, having loſt about 150 of his men killed in the place, as 'twas reported to me, and tooke many of their Armes, and ſome Colours; and of our ſide not one man killed, onely one man ſhot but not dead; thus God yet preſerves us miraculouſly, and why we ſhould diſtruſt him who deales thus for us I know not.</p>
               <p>It is thought by ſome, that <hi>Preſton</hi> had a deſigne upon <hi>Dublin,</hi> comming ſo neare it with ſuch an Army, and having no Enemy, or other place to looke for thereabouts.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Dublin,</hi> 
                     <date>July 5, 1643.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Written againe from thence by the ſame hand, being a man of credit and worth in the City of <hi>Dublin.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Wrote in my laſt how Colonell <hi>Muncke</hi> had beaten <hi>Preston,</hi> but not being able to purſue him, he having ſo ſmall a party and wanting meanes, he marched into the Counties of <hi>Wickloe</hi> and <hi>Wexford,</hi> and as he returned burnt moſt of the Towne of <hi>Arckloe,</hi> but the Caſtle there was too well fortified for him to deale with, he returned home to <hi>Dublin</hi> the laſt Munday, and brought with him about 500 Cowes, which he gave amongſt the Souldiers: In the meane time <hi>Preſton</hi> tooke in <hi>Crohan</hi> and <hi>Edenderry</hi> in the Kings County, and is now marching againe towards Caſtle <hi>Iordan</hi> to beſiege it.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:96993:2"/>
               <p>Though Captaine <hi>Bartlet</hi> came to us the laſt weeke with that proviſion which the Parliament ſent us, yet our Commanders ſay, they cannot ſtirre without 5 or 6000<hi rend="sup">lb</hi>. to provide for their traine of Artillery, for Carria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, for Shooes for the Souldiers, and ſuch like neceſſaries, which money when and how it will be gotten here none knowes, the Proteſtants eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially are ſo drained, that they have little or nothing left, and the Papiſts will lend nothing.</p>
               <p>The Rebels agree well together, ſo doe not we, and if we ſpend time about private differences one with another, and ſeeking to charge and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermine our ſelves, what muſt become of the publike.</p>
               <p>It is ſtill confirmed, that there are no Rebels to be ſeene in <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> and that the <hi>Iriſh</hi> that are there, are ſo miſerable that they eate their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and one another, a juſt judgement of God upon them for their cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Owen Roe ô Neale</hi> their Generall in that Province, with all his men are ſaid to be gone into <hi>Connaught,</hi> and that the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Army is gone after him, but I heare of no meſſage ſent by them to our State here of it, ſo that what they will doe we know not, onely of this I am ſure, if things were now well followed by them, as they might be, and that we had but ſome money for the Officers, Victuall and Ammunition, and that well ordered and governed as it ſhould be, we might by Gods help breake the heart of this Warre in a very ſhort time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bartlet</hi> came in a bleſſed time, for in that time upon a ſtrickt ſearch in <hi>Dublin,</hi> there was but 400 Barrels of Corne found in the whole City for all the Army and Inhabitants here, multitudes of the poore <hi>Engliſh</hi> come ſtill from <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter</hi> and other parts, as they get from the Rebels, which fills us with famine.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Dublin,</hi> 
                     <date>12 July, 1643.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>From the ſame hand.</head>
               <p>THat proviſion of Victuals brought by <hi>Bartlet</hi> was a meanes of keeping us from a deſolation which then was falling upon us; but that is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſpent, and we ſhall ſuddenly fall into the ſame caſe againe, if we be not ſupplied; and if we ſhall be ſupplied in time with neceſſaries, there is no doubt but by Gods bleſſing we may have a quick end of the Warre for the maine of it; for <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter</hi> is already upon the matter conquered, and no Rebels in a body to be now ſeene there. The <hi>Pale</hi> is ſo waſted, that ſcarce a Cow, Garron or Man is to be ſeene in many miles together,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96993:3"/>and the eares of the Corne which is now growing in many of theſe parts, is ſo generally cut off now before it is ripe, by the hunger-ſtarved Rebels, that very little of it will be reaped, ſo that if we could have reaſonable ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies for the preſent, that we might be able to take away this harveſt from them, and deſtroy that which we could not take, a great part of this Warre would be ended this Winter, which otherwiſe may long trouble us.</p>
               <p>You muſt know, that Souldiers which ſerve in a Countrey onely for their pay, and have no intereſt in it, will not care ſo much what becomes of it, and will exclaime more for the want of their pay if it be wanting, then thoſe who are intereſſed in it, and have hopes to recover their antient poſſeſſions and rights, of which ſort I would we had more here.</p>
               <p>Doe not forget what I now write, that the ſending of help to us now in time, will be more, then ten times ſo much when it is late, and when matters are brought to that exigent, that we ſhll be like to thoſe in a deepe conſumption which cannot be recovered.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brent</hi> the Popiſh Lawyer is ſuddenly expected here from <hi>Oxford;</hi> and at his comming ſome alterations and changes amongſt us here to follow.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Preſton</hi> we heare is about <hi>Tecrohan,</hi> threatens the Gariſon at <hi>Trim,</hi> our Army is gone that way, my Lord Marqueſſe in perſon is to follow pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, God bleſſe and proſper him.</p>
               <p>You will ſell good bargaines of our Cities and Townes here certainely when they ſhall be gained. I doe not thinke it will be two yeares pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and I thinke if things may goe on roundly, before this ſummer is ſpent, the worke would eaſily by Gods help be done, but if you looſe time a little longer, inſtead of getting any thing, both you and we ſhall be ſure to looſe all, two Moneths more of ſuch times as we have had the two laſt Moneths paſt, will doe much to bring us into a hecticke Fever, which Phiſitians ſay is irrecoverable.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Dublin,</hi> 
                     <date>July 19, 1643.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>From another good hand from <hi>Dublin.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WE know not how to live, there are now here ſuch an infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of poore people come to this Towne, which have bin ſent by the Rogues from the Garriſone which they have taken from us, that it would grieve the heart of any Chriſtian to ſee them lye in the ſtreetes ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and no means to help them. Our Army is now going forth, God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper them. Our Souldiers are in great diſtreſſe, not having either Meate, Money, Cloathes or Shoos to their feet, it is a lamentable thing to ſee what diſtreſſe they are in. The North is cleared, I wiſh their Forces were with us.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:96993:3"/>
               <head>Reaſons delivered in <hi>Ireland,</hi> againſt the Ceſſation of Armes there ſo much preſſed by the Rebels, the Treaty now broken off.</head>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1.</hi> WHereas a Ceſſation is treated of, and the only reaſon thereof, becauſe by that we muſt ſecke our ſubſiſtence; This muſt infallibly ſtarve us and the Army, Now there being many hands and active wits in ſeverall places, who doe often get ſomething by force and ſo live, then they must take nothing, but muſt only truſt to the dole of the falſe Rebels who themſelves are poore and warning.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Now our Souldiers grow in martial exerciſes and action, then they ſhall grow dull, ſick and idle to their deſtruction, ſell their Armes not cared for by their Officers, who doe ſo ill looke to them now as they loſe them and embeſle them daily.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3.</hi> The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Souldiers will runne away into <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> will be taken in their roomes, all will be <hi>Iriſh</hi> in a yeares ſpace, which is the time of Ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, especially a peace being expected, and ſo we ſhall have no Army <hi>Engliſh</hi> Horſe or Foote, whereby we ſhall be altogether at the will of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> as is deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, or elſe the <hi>Engliſh</hi> will ſtraggle to their old dwellings, and ſo be murthered here and there.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4.</hi> The Churles ſhall murther us in every corner, and the prime men not ſeene in it, where ſhall we have remedy, their being no judge nor party anſwerable, the Law not current, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> faithleſſe and really tyed to nothing.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5.</hi> The Garriſons in ſever all places have neither Corne nor Cattell, they must take none by force, how ſhall they live? the contribution cannot or will not come in, what remedy? The Rebels will have all the Corne this harveſt, we must buy it of them, and are not able for want of money, how then?</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6.</hi> The Rebell is now in great want of Corne, Ammunition, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> this harveſt and a whole yeares time, by the Sea will provide them of all things, and ſo if we ſhall have men to fight with them (which we may well doubt) they will by this furniſh and enable themſelves for <hi>2</hi> or <hi>3</hi> Yeares further at least, and ſo tire us and <hi>England,</hi> whereas it were our wiſedome to loſe no time.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>7.</hi> The <hi>Iriſh</hi> will come into <hi>Dublin,</hi> and very likely ſurpriſe us, if not, they will ſue us for any thing we owe, if we ſue them, there is no Law nor Officers to execute judgements, and if they doe not ſurprize us or pinch us with ſuites, they will ſtarve us.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <hi>8.</hi> Our little Ammunition we have will be spent before winter in ordinary watches, we have nothing to acquire more, ſo that if <hi>England</hi> helpe us not one wayes or other, this next winter we ſhall be at the will of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> as is deſired.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:96993:4"/>
               <p n="9">
                  <hi>9.</hi> Now they ſee our Army and <hi>Dublin</hi> only ſtands in the way, theſe two muſt by this deviſe unfallibly be deſtroyed by what is above ſaid, So no helpe but a new conqueſt upon moſt extreame diſadvantages if not impoſſible.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>10.</hi> The Ceſſation is for a long time, and able to give ſcope to all manner of practiſes wherein they will never ſleepe, and we by authority or inherent neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence utterly lull aſleepe; The blood of ſo many innocent <hi>Engliſh</hi> now in the heate of action being almoſt growne cold, by this deviſe a whole yeare will be given to wrap it into more oblivion, and ſo the <hi>Iriſh</hi> ſhall have their will both in Religion and poſſeſſions of our goods and Lands.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>11.</hi> When our Army by this long idleneſſe is made <hi>Iriſh</hi> or unſerviceable, if it be ſaid we will have new Armies, and not truſt the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> Then must we fight with raw Souldiers againſt experienced and better armed men, which will be dangerous, beſides the great increaſe of the charge more then now it would be.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>12.</hi> Can any man expect that the Rebels whoſe onely aime is to extirpate the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and Religion, will keepe better faith with us now, when the <hi>Engliſh</hi> are wonderfull few and diſabled, then they did when the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were in all parts, the governement ſtrong, and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> inhabitants rich and in vigour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>13.</hi> The advantage is apparently now on our ſide, the <hi>Iriſh</hi> are every where beaten, they are diſtreſſed in Victuals and Ammunition, they have no For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine aides, they feare our Armies every where, and undoubtedly by a little ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence out of <hi>England,</hi> we are able to conſume them, but by this deviſe all will be turned the other way.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>14.</hi> If a peace ſhould enſue this prologue, which is certainely expected, then the <hi>Engliſh</hi> are certainely deſtroyed, for the <hi>Iriſh</hi> continuing in their full mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes and fully armed, will be maſters both of governement and intereſt both of King and Subject, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> cannot inhabit here.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>15.</hi> This Ceſſation cannot give us Corne till harveſt, in the meane time wee ſtarve, though they ſtrive to ſend us in Cattell, which is much doubted they can very hardly doe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>16.</hi> The Ceſſation will provide onely for the Army, and that in a ſcant mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, not enough to ſerve halfe the yeare, what ſhall the poore <hi>Engliſh</hi> robbed ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects doe, they have neither money nor meanes to buy foode, but the <hi>Engliſh</hi> muſt all be gone, which is the principall labour of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> and of thoſe that have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted this Ceſſation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>17.</hi> If all the Armes of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> mighe have bin delivered up, and the Towns rendered to us, we might perhaps have had a little breathing, but no ſecurity, ſo long as ſuch huge numbers of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> remaine, and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in ſuch paucity and weakeneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>18.</hi> This Ceſſation will utterly deface our Religion, and ſet up Popery in the full height.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:96993:4"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>19.</hi> The harveſt ſaved to them and loſt to us, will be of much greater value to them for the ſubſistence and advantage, then all that they can give us can be to us, beſides the lengthening of the warre for many yeares.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>20.</hi> Their malice is now more and their power more then at the beginning, can we thinke they will hold longer with us then they ſee their time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>21.</hi> This Ceſſation leades to a peace, and being as is principally pretènded by reaſon of our extreame neceſſities and the failer of the Parliament, even to ſave our lives: whereas in truth our lives are not worth the diſhonour and detriment it will bring to the Crowne and <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, and it must worke to baſe ends, even to give the <hi>Iriſh</hi> all the Lands, and for ever keepe out the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> which is the thing mainely affected, and to worke the diſſolving of the Act for the Adventurers, and to ſmother all the cruelties, murthers and rapines committed by the <hi>Iriſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>22.</hi> It doth utterly diſcourage all the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and makes them forſake the Kingdome all they can which will ſoone be done.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>23.</hi> The Rogues of this Rebellion (though not ſeemingly countenanced by the great ones) being needy and in want, will steale all our Cowes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> from our gariſons and no remedy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>24.</hi> The Ceſſation hath in pretence an aime at our ſubſiſtence, and to be foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded only on our neceſſities, which truly is a dangerous ground of peace, amongſt ſo perſidious a people: but the inward meaning is the preſervation and reſtitution of the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and keeping out the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> governement, neither doth it ſeeme to be a thing ſo reſolutely commanded by the King, for it hath bin ſaid openly, if we would lend <hi>10000<hi rend="sup">lb</hi>.</hi> there ſhould be no Ceſſation, and yet the King ſhould be ſatisfied, or if we would propound any other way for maintenance, the like ſhould be done.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>25.</hi> It is a certaine way to loſe <hi>Ulſter,</hi> which is now in a manner intirely in our hands, and we in a faire way to <hi>Connaught.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>26.</hi> New the Cattell which we gaine though they be ſold deare here, yet our Souldiers have the money who spend it amongſt us, but if the Ceſſation proceed, then we muſt buy Corne and Cattell from the Rebels who will have all our money.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>27.</hi> Laſtly, Although we are truely in a moſt miſerable caſe for ſubſiſtence, gaſping daily for the laſt breath by ſamine or our owne enemies Sword, ſeeming for a time to be left by the Parliament through the intemperate exclamations of a wanting Army, and our Soveraigne Lord the King not able at the preſent to helpe us, Yet doubtleſſe it is leſſe diſhonourable and ſhall render us leſſe ſcandalous to poſterity to die with our Swords in our hands, yet expecting Gods mercy, then by a craved Ceſſation and in a certaine deſtruction, to tye up our hands now hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping us a little, and yeild up our ſelves and the Kingdome againſt his Majeſty
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:96993:5"/>and the Crowne of England, into the hands of barbarous Rebells, who thirſt only to riot in the blood of innocent <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and the utter abolition of the Protestant Religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The new Oath made by the ſupreame Councell of the Rebels of <hi>IRELAND</hi> at <hi>Kilkenny.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHereas the Romiſh Catholiques of this Kingdome of <hi>Ireland</hi> have bin enforced to take Armes, for the neceſſary defence and preſervation as well of the Religion plotted, and by manifold practiſes endeavoured to be quite ſuppreſſed by the Puritan faction, as likewiſe the lives, eſtates and liberties, as alſo for the defence and ſafeguard of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties regall Powers, juſt Prerogatives, Honours, Eſtates and Rights in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded upon, And for that it is requiſite that there ſhould be an unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous conſent and reall union between all the Catholiques of this Realme, to maintaine the premiſes, and ſtrengthen them againſt the Adverſaries; It is thought fit that they and whoſoever ſhall adhere to their parties as a confederate, ſhould for the better aſſurance of the adhering fidelity and conſtancy for the publike cauſe take this enſuing Oath.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>I A. B.</hi> Doe promiſe, ſweare and proteſt before God and his Saints and Angels, that I will beare faith and Allegiance to our Soveraigne Lord <hi>Charles,</hi> by the grace of God, King of Great-<hi>Brittany, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and to his Pleyres and lawfull Succeſſors, and that I will to my power during my life, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, uphold and maintaine all his and their juſt Prerogatives, Eſtates and Rights, the Power and Priviledge of the Parliament of this Realme, the fundamentall Lawes of <hi>Ireland,</hi> the free exerciſe of the Catholique Romiſh Faith and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion throughout this Land, and the Lives, juſt Liberties, Poſſeſſions, Eſtates and Rights of all thoſe that have taken or ſhall take this Oath, and performe the contents thereof: And that I will obey and ratiſie all the Orders and Decrees made and to be made by the ſuprcame Councell of the confederate Catholiques of this Kingdome concerning the publike cauſe. And that I will not ſeeke or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive directly or indirectly, any pardon or protection for any act done or to be done touching this generall cauſe, without the conſent of the major part of the ſaid Councell: And that I will not directly or indirectly doe any act or acts that ſhall prejudice the ſaid Cauſe, but will to the hazard of my life and eſtate, aſſiſt, proſecute and maintaine the ſame. So helpe me God and his holy Goſpell.</q>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:96993:5"/>
               <head>Killmore Caſtle in <hi>Ireland,</hi> Iune <hi>23, 1643.</hi> A Letter from Sir <hi>Robert Stewart</hi> Knight and Colonell to the Earle of <hi>Eglington.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Right Honourable, and my very Noble Lord,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOur Lordſhips I received the very ſame day before Sir <hi>William Stow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>art</hi> and I, with the reſt of the Forces here, tooke our march upon a late expedition to the Counties of <hi>Monoghan</hi> and <hi>Tirone,</hi> for the which and all your Lordſhips kind expreſſions unto me, I give your Lordſhip ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hearty thanks, and am your Lordſhips moſt humble ſervant; and for what happened in the ſame expedition, your Lordſhip ſhall have the true Relation of it as followeth; and firſt when Sir <hi>William Stewarts</hi> Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Colonell <hi>Mervins,</hi> and mine owne, with five Companies out of <hi>Derry</hi> had marched a day or two together, we had intelligence that <hi>Owen Mac Art ô Neale</hi> the Rebels great titulary Generall had drawn all the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter</hi> together, with their whole Cowes, and was upon their march for <hi>Connoght,</hi> of purpoſe as we were informed to leave his weake people there and all their Cattell, and to returne himſelfe with a ſtrong Army to aſſault us and the reſt of the <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Army in <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> upon which intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence we haſtned our march to a place where we heard that he was to march through, a place called <hi>Clownys</hi> in the County of <hi>Monnoghan,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the roade way from <hi>Tirone</hi> to <hi>Connaught,</hi> and about ſome 25 miles diſtant from <hi>Charlemount,</hi> and through Gods providence it fell out, that upon the 13 of this inſtant <hi>June,</hi> a Scout of Horſe which I ſent out (I having the Van that day) diſcovered the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army, upon the which I gave order that our Army in regard of their hard march formerly, ſhould refreſh themſelves with one houre or two's reſt, which was done accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, and ſo we ſtrengthened our Porlorne guard, and ſo continued our march towards them; whenas we advanced neare unto them, we diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered their Horſe drawne up upon a peece of ground of advantage, and from them were commanded out a party of their beſt Horſe very well mounted, which in a daring inſulting way came up and charged ſome of my Troope, which they received very reſolutely, and after a whiles diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute they were put to a retreate, in this interim, a party of the Rebels Foote had drawne up into a place where was a narrow ſtone cauſey and ſtraight paſſe, where they thought to keepe up our Horſe, but was put from it by our commanded men, and ſo the paſſe was cleered, and my Troope being ſeconded by Sir <hi>William Stewarts</hi> Troope and Sir <hi>William Belfores,</hi> advanced forward upon their Horſes, and our commanded men on both ſides gave very good fire upon one another, the way where the reſt of our Army marched was very narrow, ſo that none of them came to doe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:96993:6"/>exce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt only the ſirſt diviſion of my Regiment, which I led on my ſelfe, and before ever the ſecond diviſion came to my ſervice, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that there was 11 Colours of the Rebels upon ſervice all the while, the Rebels was routed both Foote and Horſe, and our light wings and Cannons did very good ſervice, and many of the chiefeſt and beſt of their Forraigne Officers were either killed in the filds or taken priſoners, for our Horſe had the killing of them for 8 or 9 miles together upon all hands, and our Foote for 5 miles or thereabouts, where was done great execution upon the beſt of their men, <hi>Owen Mac Art ô Neale</hi> himſelfe very narrowly eſcaped, for the Captaine of my Troope was in gripes with him, but his Horſe ſtumbled and he was hurt with a ſhot, and <hi>Owen Mac Art</hi> was releeved by one of his Captaines. One <hi>ô Mellane</hi> who is now pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned with me, ſeverall other priſoners I have, as one Colonell <hi>Brother,</hi> ſonne to <hi>Owen Mac Art</hi> and bred a Souldier, borne in <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> another Lieutenanr Colonell who hath bin an Officer abroad this 24 Yeares, cal-<hi>Shane ô Neale,</hi> 3 Captaines, Named <hi>Art ô Neale, Shane ô Neale</hi> and <hi>Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick ô Mullin,</hi> and 3 Gentlemen of quality, Named <hi>William ô Clenton, Manns ô Sheale,</hi> and <hi>Con ô Neale,</hi> great ſtore of Armes we had both for Horſe and Foote, and I beleeve they carried few with them, for my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment had 300 Muskets for their ſhare, beſides many Swords, Petro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels and Piſtolls, beſides all that the reſt of the Regiments had. That night <hi>Owen Mac Art</hi> himſelfe betooke him to a Wood, where was a Friery within 7 or 8 miles to <hi>Charlemount,</hi> where he lodged that night with ſix only in his company, as I was informed by a party of mine which I ſent out the next morning to that ſame Wood, but before they came they were unfortunately eſcaped, and my men burnt the Friery and brought away a great prey of Cowes with them, and ſo ſpent 7 or 8 dayes in ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the Countrey, good numbers every day of ſcattered Roagues we killed in woods, Boggs and Mountaines, the ſtrength of the Rebels Army was neere 3000 good men, by relation of ſome of themſelves who now are Priſoners, beſides thoſe that were with the Cowes, thus giving glory to God Almighty in whoſe power it is with few to defeate a great many, this being the true Relation, wiſhing your Lordſhip all health and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, I reſt</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Lordſhips loving and obedient ſervant <hi>Robert Stewart.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>They had 32 Colours, with 3000 Foote, and 300 Horſe.</p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:96993:6"/>
               <head>A Letter written by <hi>Owen Mac Art ô Neale</hi> the day after they loſt this Batell, unto Sir <hi>Robert Stewart.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Should intreate you to be pleaſed for to certifie unto me by this bearer what priſoners you have taken or have in reſtraint of ours ſince the other day, together with your demands, whether you will exchange them for any Priſoners wee have, or if for Ranſome, how much, wherein you ſhall doe me a curteſie, and to your ſelfe no hurt, for now though Fortune be favourable unto you, it may chance fall out hereafter, that your kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and favour therein may be requited, if ever it comes in the way of</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your aſſured Friend as I find you <hi>Owen ô Neale.</hi>
                  </signed>
                  <dateline>From our Campe <date>the 16 of <hi>June,</hi> 1643.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>This Campe was only himſelfe and 5 or 6 more.</p>
                  <p>I pray let this bearer ſee the priſoners.</p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>By a Letter dated the <hi>20</hi> of <hi>June, 1643.</hi> From <hi>London-derry</hi> it is thus written by Captaine <hi>Henry Finch</hi> of the ſaid City.</head>
               <p>THat upon the twelfth of the ſaid <hi>June,</hi> 600 choſen men out of that City, and 60 Horſe joyned with Regunents of Sir <hi>Robert</hi> and Sir <hi>William Stewart,</hi> and Colonell <hi>Audley Mervin,</hi> who met with <hi>Art Mac ô Neale</hi> the Generall of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Forces in <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> and all his ſtrength, neare a Towne called <hi>Clownes,</hi> about 50 miles from our ſaid City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don-derry,</hi> where but a part of our Army being drawne up had a glorious day, ſlew 500 of the Rebles in the place, whereof 150 Commanders and Gentlemen of their prime, who fought couragiouſly for their lives: We tooke priſoners who are now in our Jayle, <hi>Hugh ô Neale</hi> Colonell, <hi>Shane ô Neale,</hi> Lieutenant Colonell,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Art ô Neale,</hi> Captaines.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Shane ô Neale,</hi> Captaines.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pattrick ô Mullin,</hi> Captaines.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William O clinton</hi> Lieutenant.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Manus ô Sheile,</hi> Gentlemen.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Con ô Neale,</hi> Gentlemen.</item>
                  </list> All men of prime note and very conſiderable, we loſt only 6 or 8 Troo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, but many dangerouſly hurt, where of Sir <hi>William Stewarts</hi> ſome was
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:96993:7"/>and Captaine <hi>Garthconte,</hi> Captaine of Sir <hi>Roberts</hi> Troope, and other men who came bravely on that day: It was a great Victory, and neere a breake-neck to the <hi>Northerne</hi> Forces of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels, It was Gods doing, 500 of our men did not fight for it, the greateſt part of our Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my not ſo much as ſeeing the Enemy but upon the flight, and dead, we had the chaſe 6 or 8 miles in good ground, in the march out and home we killed above 500 more of the Rebels. We have now no conſiderable Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my within 40 or 50 miles of us, but we are ſo ſtraightned for proviſion Victuals and Match, Pouder and all other Ammunition, that we cannot keepe the Fields long, had our Army bin there or provided, we had clee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Tyrone</hi> before our returne, but we had no bread in three dayes, and our Match, Pouder and other proviſions were ſpent; ſo againſt our wills, for want thereof, were forced to returne home. We have made ſo many mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches this Summer into <hi>Donagale, Tyrone</hi> and <hi>London-derry,</hi> that there is lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or no proviſions left in the Countrey, and few or no Rogues to be ſeen, all either killed or fled into <hi>Connought,</hi> but great ſtore of women and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, whereof few Cabbins in our march was empty, in ſome 5, in ſome 10 and in ſome 20 found dead in a Cabbin, part of them eaten by the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, it is a moſt lamentable caſe they have brought themſelves unto.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Dublin 12 July,</hi> From another hand.</head>
               <p>I Have bin out with the Army this 5 Weekes, or els I had written unto you before now: whiles we were abroad we tooke the Lord <hi>Dempſyes</hi> Caſtle, and blew it up. which was a very ſtrong hold and nurſerie of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, and one <hi>Fitz Garrets</hi> Caſtle of <hi>Clorboly</hi> we tooke and blew up, and one other of the <hi>Fitz Garrets</hi> yeelded his upon quarter, and had halfe his Armes, and as much goods as he could carry away, we got above 2000 Cowes in <hi>Wickloe,</hi> the Lord <hi>Moore</hi> hath gotten 7000 Cowes another way, the poore Rogues are ſtarving, for they have nothing in moſt parts hereabours, but Horſes and Weedes to live on.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A Letter from <hi>Dublin</hi> of the <hi>12</hi> of <hi>July, 1643.</hi> from a man of worth to his Friend in London; Concerning the Earle of <hi>Ormends</hi> carriage in the matter of Ceſſation deſired by the Rebels.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>SOme Letters of yours I have received, but divers I beleeve have miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carried, through the Sea Captaine Mr. <hi>Plunkets</hi> miſtake, or knowing,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:96993:7"/>for to both he is very ſubject. I am ſhrewdly tempted to tell you, that mine to you have runne the ſame fortune, but the truth is, this is the firſt I could find time or reaſon to write ſince you went, I know you have heard gallant things of the Lord Marqueſſe of <hi>Ormond</hi> there touching a Treaty he had with the Rebels about a Ceſſation of Armes; and I make no doubt he is ſet forth from hence in the true ſhape and colour of a Rebell, or at leaſt a lover of Rebels, there is no man to whom he hath more cleere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly decared himſelfe, touching his thoughts of, and intentions towards them, then my ſelfe: And beleeve me, hee is juſt where you left him, nothing changed, either in good will or bitterneſſe towards them, when he went to Treate with them, he had by the favour of the Lords Juſtices and Counſell, ſome of the Board to goe with him, and he deſired ſome chiefe Officers of the Army with them, to be witneſſes of his carriage through the whole matter, which what ever end it take, I beleeve it will be printed, when firſt ſome of his good friends here, have written their conjectures of it; in the meane time, the maine matter that is like to be ſuggeſted to his prejudice, is, that this Treaty was not only performed, but deſired and wholy gained from the King by his meanes and advice: His Lordſhip hath learnt by Sir <hi>Benjamin Rudyards</hi> ſpeech, about the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of this Parliament, how unhanſome it is to juſtifie unpleaſing things, by putting them upon the King, and therefore I ſhould ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of that in his behalfe, but that to you, I deſire to give ſatisfaction, that there is nothing falſer, except him that ſhall write it, and having ſaid this, I ſhall trouble you no more in that point.</p>
               <p>One other thing is ſo much talked of here, that I owe his Lordſhip the right, and you who are my friend the ſatisfaction; To acquaint you with his carriage in it. Very ſoon after your departure hence, the Captaine of the Swallow and others of that company came aſhoare, amongſt the reſt the Maſter, who ſtayed late at the Globe Taverne, ſo late, that the Maſter of the houſe againſt his owne profit, deſired him and his company to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, which when they refuſed, he likewiſe refuſed to give them wine, and at length being deſirous to be quit of them, he ſent for a guard to take them away, which accordingly was done, and the Maſter ſent to the Main-guard, where the Captaine being in like diſorder, as I heare, not only miſuſed the man, but ſpake diſgracefully of the Parliament, the Earles of <hi>Eſſex</hi> and <hi>Warwick</hi> as is alledged, now his Lordſhips ſhare of the matter is as followes, the Captaine came to him and complained of this uſage, and when his Lordſhip told him he was ready to doe him juſtice as ſoone as the matter would give him ground for it by petitioning, he ſaid he tooke it to be the better way to paſſe it over, ſithence he found the Officers
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:96993:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>were generally ſo diſcontened, as that the ſtirring of this might prove the occaſion of more diſorder, and be a meanes to ſpread the matter further then hee deſired, to that his Lordſhip anſwered, that hee knew beſt what hee had to doe, but that hee was ready upon complaint as afore-ſaid to doe his part towards the vindication of the juſtice of this place, and of any perſon injured here, but approved of his m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations to ſmother a buſineſſe of that unpleaſing nature, this diſcourſe paſt betweene his Lordſhip and him in my hearing, when it was ended he went away as I thought, reſolved to ſay no more of the matter, but a little before his going hence, when he had taken other advice, he prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red an Information into the Martiall Court againſt him who was the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the watch night, but there left it without any man to follow it, where it ſtill remaines ready for further ſcanning, when any man ſhall call upon it, and ſo much for that. If I ſhould take upon me to anſwer all the lies raiſed on his Lordſhip here, by the father of lies and his hopefull iſſue, I ſhould become the greateſt writer of this age, and therefore I leave them to the ſhame I know will one day overtake them, reſting</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your moſt faithfull friend and humble ſervant <hi>I B.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Letter from the ſame man from <hi>Dublin, 20 July, 1643.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Have according to my improvident cuſtome, deſerted writing till this laſt minute of time, haveing bin for ſome dayes imployed in ſetting on a preſent march, which hath bin infinitely retarded and diſtracted through the miſerable want of all things, now at length the buſineſſe hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded, that together with ſome Forces appointed to meete from <hi>Drog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heda, Trim</hi> and <hi>Dundalke,</hi> and a party ſent hence afore, there will be about 4000 ſighting men, Horſe and Foote, the latter pittifull poore, but as they are, I hope they will ſtop <hi>Preſton</hi> in the courſe of his proceeding againſt our Garriſons, whereof he hath poſſeſſed himſelfe of one, which was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted by the men and burnt, other places where there were wards be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to private perſons, were rendered without reſiſtance, as <hi>Eden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derry</hi> and <hi>Techrohan,</hi> and now Caſtle <hi>Jordan</hi> and another place is in danger, which to prevent, my Lord Marqueſſe doth goe after the Army to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, but his proportion of victuall not being for many weekes, he is tyed to a very ſhort time for the worke which his Lordſhip will attempt, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:96993:8"/>leave the ſucceſſe to God, this I tell you, that your expectation be not raiſed above what is poſſible to be effected: two packquets from hence were taken by the <hi>Wexford men,</hi> wherein they boaſt to have found great mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries; and I feare by thoſe Letters they have found too much of diviſion amongſt us, for calumnies, complaints and accuſations are ſo frequent Theames of ſome diſpatches thether, which may incourage the Rebels, and diſpoſe them to unite in much the worſer cauſe, for even now I have adveriſement that <hi>Preſton</hi> hath poſſeſt himſelfe of all the paſſages into that faſt Countrey, except what lyeth behind him, whereto I feare his Lordſhip ſhall want bread to march, nor were it fit to leave him neerer this Towne then our ſelves, the condition of the inhabitants duly conſidered, and Caſtle <hi>Jordan</hi> for <hi>Dublin</hi> being but a bad exchange, ſo that upon the whole matter, hard are the tearmes his Lordſhip goes upon and in this harder then any mans, in that the good ſhall be imputed to others, if it pleaſe God to bleſſe the Army with ſucceſſe, and if any miſchance hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens (which is not impoſſible) his Lordſhip I feare muſt beare it, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all the malitious conſtructions that can be made, theſe have bin his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips incouragements ſince he had the honour to ſerve the King in theſe imployments, but I can aſſure you that doth not diſcourage him, nor will any thing elſe, that can be raiſe or done here or there, I am</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your very faithfull friend and ſervant <hi>I. B.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Another Letter from a very good hand in <hi>Dublin,</hi> dated <hi>19, July, 1633.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YOur Letter lately received here and ſome ſmall quantity of victuals ſent hither, perſwades me, that we are not wholly deſerted by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, though I muſt tell you, ſo barely and coldly remembred, that if a better and ferventer regard be not timely had of us, nothing in humane reaſon can be expected but abſolute ruine, and deſtruction of the beſt parts of the Kingdome.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Preſton</hi> with his Forces of 7000 Foote and 800 Horſe, ſuperiour unto us in Cavelry, and Armes doubling our ſtrength that is here, or that can conveniently be drawn together from or neereſt Garriſons: is now in the County of <hi>Meath,</hi> hath taken Sir <hi>William Coolies</hi> Caſtle, and ſeverall other holds, have endeavoured to block up Caſtle <hi>Jordan,</hi> and is quartered at this time about <hi>Tecrohan,</hi> Sir <hi>Lucas Fitz Gerralds,</hi> with intention, as our intelligence brings us to take in <hi>Trim, Manooth,</hi> or both of them, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure vaſter purpoſes.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:96993:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Ten dayes we have travelled in all the faire and foule wayes that can be invented to raiſe a ſmall ſumme of money to ſet forth our Army, but are not yet at the end of our journey, two dayes more I hope will finiſh it, and then my Lord Marqueſſe goes forth in perſon, I pray God proſper him.</p>
               <p>The harveſt is now beginning, but before the ſickle comes to the Corne, moſt of it is devoured by the ſtarving people, and that in truth is the beſt expedient to end this Warre, and ſoone will doe it, if our Army, and the ſmall remnant of our Nation remaining here may be aſcertained of food from <hi>England;</hi> and Pouder and Armes are all moſt as neceſſary; labour theſe two as you love the peace of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> ſuch is the ſute and deſire of</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your humble ſervant <hi>T. H.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A true Relation of the manner of our Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell Sir <hi>Frederick Hamiltons</hi> returne from <hi>London-derry</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> being 60 miles from his Caſtle and Garriſon, where he was at the beginning and breaking out of this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, with the particular ſervices performed by the <hi>Horſe and Foote Companies which he commandes</hi> garriſon'd at <hi>Manor Hamilton</hi> in the County of <hi>Leinim</hi> in the Province of <hi>Connaught.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Iron workes called the Garriſon within ſix miles to <hi>Hamil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> Caſtle,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tober <hi>24</hi>
                  </note> was by the <hi>O flannygans,</hi> of the County of <hi>Fermannagh,</hi> and the <hi>Mac Laughlins</hi> and <hi>Mac Murrayes,</hi> of the the County of <hi>Leytrim,</hi> ſet on ſire and all burned.</p>
               <p>Seven or eight ſcore men,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ober <hi>24</hi>
                  </note> women and children, moſt of them <hi>Engliſh,</hi> belonging to thoſe Iron workes, were divers of them ſore wounded, all of them robbed, came flying for reliefe to Caſtle <hi>Hamilton,</hi> where the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonels Lady charitably received them, himſelfe and his two ſonnes at that time being at <hi>London-derry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This newes coming this day fortunately by a meſſenger from his Lady,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ober</note> he deſperately adventured homewards with 10 or 12 Horſe of his owne ſervants, paſſing over <hi>Barneſmore</hi> in the night time with every Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man his Calliver and his Match light at both ends, with ſound of Trumpet
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:96993:9"/>moſt part of the night as we marched, making a great ſhew and a noyſe as if an Army had followed us. Thus it pleaſed Gos we paſſed 30 miles of our way that night, coming to <hi>Donegall</hi> the next morning.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Donegall</hi> we found Sir <hi>Raph Gore,</hi> Mr. <hi>Brooke,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Octobr <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> and all the Brittiſh of that part of the County, robbed of their Cattell, ſhortly expecting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be deſtroyed, much admiring if we had bin 500 men, how we durſt have paſt <hi>Barneſmore,</hi> adviſing our Colonell to adventure no further homewards, <hi>Ballyſhannon</hi> Caſtle in his way homewards being block't up with a great many <hi>Engliſh</hi> in it, and that Towne bruned.</p>
               <p>That night nevertheleſſe did we paſſe with a Convoy only of 20 <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh</hi> Horſemen to <hi>Ballyſhannon,</hi> relieving that Caſtle, preſently calling out Captaine <hi>Follyot</hi> with ſome few men for our guides, went a hunting for the Rogues, who had beene lately about the Caſtle, where that night ere we lighted we killed ſome of them, and brought home 22 Priſoners. That night out Colonell diſpatched a meſſenger to his Lady being 12 miles. It pleaſed God ſo to bleſſe his meſſenger, that the next morning by day his Lady ſent him a good guard of his owne Souldiers and ſervants, before the Countrey could heare of our being upon the way, which otherwiſe it had bin impoſſible for us to paſſe, having the borders of 3 Counties to march through, and that the moſt dangerous way in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Colonell is viſited by <hi>Connour ô Rourke</hi> the High Sheriff of the County of <hi>Leytrim,</hi> congratulating his ſafe returne beyond expectation,<note place="margin">Octobe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>31.</hi>
                  </note> then profeſſing much loyalty and neighbourly love which not long laſted.</p>
               <p>Came from <hi>Dublin</hi> with the Lords Juſtices paſſe ſix of our Colonells Souldiers from <hi>Carliſle,</hi> who miraculouſly paſſed without loſſe of Armes,<note place="margin">Nove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> Cleathes or what elſe they carried, to our Colonells great joy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, being ſive <hi>Scotch</hi>-men and one <hi>Iriſh</hi>-man good Musketeeres bred with himſelfe.</p>
               <p>The Colonell makes up amongſt his ſervants and Tenants,<note place="margin">Nove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> a Troope of 50 good Horſes, which doe duty day and night about the Garriſon and Caſtle.</p>
               <p>It is diſcoved to the Colonell, that one <hi>Conouroge Mac Shant,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Claſſe Mac Laughlin</hi> a moſt dangerous active man, and the chiefe of that name, was drawing of a Boate 8 miles over mountaines, thinking to have man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned an Iſland in the <hi>Lough</hi> of great conſequence, being in a great glynne called <hi>Glevedin,</hi> which Iſland in former Rebellions had much galled the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Forces, it lying convenient for the bordering Rebels both of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster</hi> and <hi>Connaught;</hi> Vpon this information a party of able Foote-men were ſent out, who met with the ſaid <hi>Connour</hi> upon the top of a great
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:96993:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>Mountaine, with a many Horſe and Foote, drawing of his Boate, where himſelfe was taken Priſoner, and his Boate broken all in pecces upon the Mountaine.</p>
               <p>The Colonell received two Letters,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>emb: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> one from <hi>O Connour</hi> of <hi>Sligo,</hi> the other from <hi>Ballagh ô Rourke,</hi> both profeſſing much loyalty, excuſing their not waiting upon him, and congratulating his late and unexpected re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne from the <hi>Derry.</hi> Theſe Letters were kindly anſwered, with encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement from the Colonell to perſevere in their loyalty, though he little expected it, as it afterwards came to paſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Con Mac Ternan bane ô Rourck,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>emb: <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </note> the moſt active and moſt dangerous man of that name: It is informed that he and others had lately robbed an <hi>Endliſh</hi>-Miniſter called Mr. <hi>Buſhe</hi> apprehended by the Colonells order.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bryan ô Rourke</hi> another prime Gentleman of that name,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>emb: 6</note> and Brther in law to the fore-ſaid <hi>Con ô Rourke,</hi> was likewiſe apprehended upon In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation that he had rob'd another <hi>Engliſh</hi>-man, <hi>William Browne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Being informed that many of the Rebels of <hi>Donegall</hi> all <hi>Firmannagh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>emb: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0</note> had their daily tandevous at an Ale-houſe kept 6 miles from our Colonels Caſtle neare the borders of <hi>Fermannagh:</hi> A party was ſent thither in the night, where the Ale-houſe keeper <hi>Cahir Mac Caba</hi> with ſix Rogues more were apprehended and brought to our Colonell, with 60 Beeves from the County, who were all in Rebellion as all the other Counties a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout us, only the two <hi>Barronyes</hi> neare to our Colonels, where his owne <hi>Jriſh</hi> Tenants lived, made ſhew of loyalty, hoping thereby to have gotten greater advantage afterwards.</p>
               <p>A Court was to have beene held by the Colonells Seneſehall,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>emb:</note> expecting his <hi>Iriſh</hi>-Tenants ſhould have made their appearance, as till that day they duly did, hee uſing all the meanes he could to preſerve his owne in their Ioyalties, as many times they faithfully promiſed, but that day abſenting themſelves, he perceived them all traitors.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hugh Mac Cahill Mac Murry</hi> the chiefe <hi>Iriſh</hi>-Tenant upon the Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nele Land,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="6 letters">
                        <desc>••••••</desc>
                     </gap>mb: <hi>30</hi>
                  </note> who had jugled with his <hi>Brittiſh</hi>-Tenants, making them believe he was a guard for their Cattell, in preſerving and recovering ſome of them which had beene ſtolne by the neighbouring Rebels, did this day joyne himſelfe with the <hi>Cavan</hi> Rebels, who in a great body march't with Drumme and Colours within two miles of our Caſtle, drawing with them a many of the <hi>Brittiſh</hi>-Tenants Cattell, and taking with them one <hi>Engliſh</hi>-man whom they hanged.</p>
               <p>The Colonell now perceiving their generall trecheries,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>b: <hi>4</hi>
                  </note> leaves off any more to truſt them, and ſeeing no order for reliefe either from the Lord Juſtices, or the Lord Preſident: They having received advertiſement from
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:96993:10"/>our Colonell not onely of the ſtate of his owne Caſtle, but alſo of the Towne and Garriſon of <hi>Sligo,</hi> where a part of the Lord Preſidents owne Company lay, with a many <hi>Brittiſh,</hi> who were miſerably murthered at the taking in of that Towne, being promiſed daily reliefe by the Lord Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident, which promiſe and encouragement as ſome of themſelves ſay, help't to deſtroy them, otherwiſe they could have joyned with us before the Rebellion there brake out in that height. This day by our Colonells command, a Gallowes was erected upon the top of an hill neare the Caſtle, and having about 24 Priſoners in the Caſtle, he cauſed 8 of them to be hanged up, which had beene at the burning of <hi>Ballyſhannon</hi> in the County of <hi>Donegall,</hi> and at the burning of the Iron workes in the County of <hi>Fermannagh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame day our Horſe-men ſcouring the ſields, tooke two of the Rogues Centries, who were brought home and hanged.</p>
               <p>A party was ſent in the night to ſcoure <hi>Glansfarne</hi> Woods,<note place="margin">Decem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> upon intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence that <hi>Hugh Mac Cahill</hi> the righleader of the Colonells traiterous Tenants kept in thoſe Woods, where indeed they were met withall, 3 of them killed, divers wounded, and their great leader narrowly eſcaping in the Woods through the darkneſſe of the night.</p>
               <p>Our Horſe-men ſcouring the fields,<note place="margin">Decem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> met with another of the Rebels Centries, who was brought to the Caſtle and hanged.</p>
               <p>One <hi>Thomas Abercromy</hi> being miſled by a treacherous Jeſuiticall kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of his owne, this day did for ſake his owne houſe,<note place="margin">Decem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> being a pretty ſtone Houſe with a Barne, within a mile of our Colonells Caſtle, tranſports himſelfe, his Wife and Children to the Caſtle of <hi>Con ô Rourk,</hi> apparently by this time in Rebellion, leaving in his owne houſe his ſaid Rapiſticall kinſman, married to an <hi>Iriſh</hi>-woman, with ſome of the ſaid <hi>Con ô Rourks Iriſh</hi> Rogues, for maintaining of that houſe, which our Colonell held no good neighouthood; He many times neighbourly and kindly inviting the ſaid <hi>Thomas Abercromy</hi> with his wife and children to take ſhare with him in his Caſtle, and not to ſhame and diſhonour himſelfe and his Nation in ſuch a kind: whoſe anſwer was, he was fully preſwaded of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of this Caſtle and all in it, for it was ſo reſolved, as he was credibly aſſured, not only by thoſe of this County, but of all the bordering Counties neare it, and that he was promiſed by the favour of the ſaid <hi>Con ô Rourke,</hi> to have his owne life with his wife and childrens preſerved untill they were elſe-where tranſported.</p>
               <p>Complaint was made to the Colonell,<note place="margin">Decem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>16.</hi>
                  </note> that ſome of this <hi>Con ô Rourkes</hi> Rogues had robbed ſome of his Tenants, ſervants and gardens, who ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding after them, had ſome of the Rogues apprehended; where little <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:96993:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>Abercromy</hi> the Papiſt preſumed to interpoſe himſelfe for the reſcuing of thoſe Rogues, as they were brought by the houſe his Coſen left him in, upon this Information our Colonell cauſed him to be apprehended as a dangerous Inſtrument there,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> the Rogues in the houſe with him running away, the houſe is demoliſhed and made unſerviceable.</p>
               <p>A party in the night time was ſent abroad towards <hi>Sligoe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>mb: <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>0</hi>
                  </note> where we met with a number of Rogues, hurt divers, killed three, brought home thcirheads to our Colonell with a luſty Priſoner, who was hanged next day.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Owne ô Rourke,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ary <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Bryan Ballagh</hi> his Brother, with the greateſt ſtrength of this County of <hi>Cavan,</hi> made a great ſhew this day, being about a 1000 or 1200 men,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>e</hi>
                  </note> marcht with Musket ſhot to us, (where from the Caſtle we ſhot one of them dead,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>6</hi>
                  </note> being a ſigne of good luck, making them march further off,) This night they encamped at <hi>Larganboye,</hi> where <hi>Abercro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes</hi> houſe was lately deſtroyed, being diſappointed of what they expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted for there,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> their chiefe Commanders marching a mile further for their quarters to <hi>Con ô Rourke</hi> the then Sheriffe, who till that day had not pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely declared himſelfe; there they found <hi>Thomas Aberoromy</hi> with his wife and children; The Rogues continued with their Campe at <hi>Lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganboy,</hi> within a mile to us, and their chiefe Officers at <hi>Con ô Rourkes,</hi> from Thurſday till Tueſday following, daily drawing out their men to the hills about us, every day multiplying, making great ſhewes, thinking thereby to have ſcared us out of the Caſtle.</p>
               <p>This morning the Sheriffe <hi>Con ô Rourke</hi> in the head of Rebels,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>ary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> marcht in a full body within halfe a mile to the Caſtle, as if he meant preſently to have aſſaulted us, which the Colonell perceiving, drawes forth in perſon as ſtrong as he could make, both Horſe and Foote, being farre ſhort of the ſixth man of their number, yet made offer there to have fought with them, which the Rogues perceiving make a halt upon a Hill a River di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding us, they calling to us that we were Rebels to the King and not they; Our Colonell wiſhing them, ſince their quarrell was ſo good and their number ſo much greater then ours, they would try it with us: In the meane time while we were thus parleying, men were ſent out by the Colonell in ſeverall quarters behind us, to ſet fire on a many goodly Houſes and haggards belonging to his owne Tenants, leaſt the Rogues with their multitudes ſhould have quartered themſelves moſt convcniently round about him, which ſodaine fire the Rogues perceiving, preſently imagined aide was come to us; The fires being up we advanct with grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter confidence, whereupon they retreated in diſorder, and diſpearſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves preſently, ſome of our Horſe-men imployed in the burning, appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:96993:11"/>two of the Rogues, which were brought to the Colonell as we drew home to the Caſtle, which by his orders were that night hanged.</p>
               <p>A party of Horſe and Foote were ſent towards the Sheriffe <hi>Con ô Rourkes</hi> Caſtle, to requite his kind viſit towards ours the day before,<note place="margin">Ianu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> where we found himſelfe, with his wife, children and family ſled that night, leaving <hi>Thomas Abercromy</hi> with his wife and children in poſſeſſion of his Caſtle, whom our Souldiers turned out, victualling themſelves with ſtore of Poudred-Beefe, Butter, Meale and ſuch like commodities, what they were able to carry away; afterwards ſetting fire in the Caſtle, and in many other thatched houſes about it, burning all.</p>
               <p>A party is ſent towards the Caſtle of <hi>Drommahere,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ianua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>13.</hi>
                  </note> where their great Colonell <hi>Owen ô Rourke</hi> with all his ſtrength lay; yet we burned many goodly houſes and haggards of Corne within a mile of the Caſtle, burning all within five miles forwards.</p>
               <p>Our party marcht Weſtwards 6 miles towards <hi>Sligo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ianua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> burning many goodly houſes and haggards that way, and amongſt them the houſe and haggards of <hi>Bryan ballagh ô Rourke,</hi> Brother to the fore-ſaid <hi>Con ô Rourke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A party of Horſe were ſent North-weſtward 6 miles towards the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of <hi>Sligo,</hi> where we burned a ſtrong ſtone houſe ſlated with a bawne,<note place="margin">Ianua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> built by Sir <hi>Roger Iones,</hi> called <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nloanes Foart;</hi> This day we alſo burned many other <hi>Iriſh</hi>-houſes and haggards, and in our retreat, we encountred amongſt the Woods a prime Rebell called <hi>Ternan oge Mac Art ô Rourke,</hi> whoſe head was brought to the Caſtle that night.</p>
               <p>A party of Foote are ſent 6 miles Northwards towards the borders of the County of <hi>Fermannagh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ianua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>16.</hi>
                  </note> burning all that way many houſes and haggards belonging to the <hi>ô Menghons, Thomas Mac Loans,</hi> and the <hi>ô Frciles</hi> of <hi>Roſſenner:</hi> The party marching homewards was betrayed by their guide, and were layed for in their march by above 300 of the Rogues, our par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty not being 60, five of our men were killed, and 8 of the Rebels, ſo this march concluded the burning of all houſes and Corne within 6 miles round about our Caſtle, not ſo much left as a Cabbin to campe in.</p>
               <p>This day the greateſt ſtrength of the Conty with the aſſiſtance of the Lord <hi>Taffes</hi> ſonne, and Captaine <hi>Bryan Mac Donnoghy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ianua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>25.</hi>
                  </note> from the County of <hi>Sligoe,</hi> the <hi>Mac Gawrans</hi> from the County of <hi>Cavan,</hi> to the number of 1200, or 1400 men, encamped themſelves at the old place <hi>Largenboy,</hi> where they lay in the Fields that night, and the next morning drave away all our Colonells Cowes to the number of 4 or 5 hundred.</p>
               <p>Having gotten our Cowes, they who tooke them came this day againe,<note place="margin">Ianua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>26.</hi>
                  </note> and encamped themſelves at two houſes, which our Colonell was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:96993:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>by his Licutenant to leave unburnt, within halfe a mile to the Caſtle, where was ſtore of Corne at one of the houſes, belonging to the Lieutenant himſelfe, which Corne the Rogues fell a burning, which much vexed us, but they lying in that manner, burning of our Corne from Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day till Tueſday, our Colonell then with a party of Horſe and Foote, did beate them from their quarters, killed 8 of them, and chaſed the reſt being five times our number.</p>
               <p>This day <hi>Owen ò Rourke,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>ary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> with the aſſiſtance of Colonell <hi>Con Mac Donnell ô Rourke</hi> and his Regiment from <hi>Iames</hi> Towne, with the <hi>ô Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors</hi> and <hi>Mac Gawrans</hi> from the Counties of <hi>Sligo</hi> and <hi>Cavan,</hi> to the number of 1500 or 1600 men burnt our Towne and Mills of <hi>Mannour Hamilton,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">ſſſar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> which day upon the Rogues retreat from that good ſervice, our Colonell not being provided otherwiſe to entertaine them, endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſafety of his people, which that day God preſerved within his Caſtle and bawne, yet cauſed he to be hanged upon the gallowes in their view, <hi>Con ô Rourke,</hi> Brother to their great Colonell <hi>Owen,</hi> and <hi>Connor Mac Laughlin</hi> chiefe of that Name, two of the ableſt and moſt dangerous men in this County.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Owen ô Rourke</hi> with his Brother <hi>Bryan Ballagh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>uary</note> and the <hi>Mac Glanna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hans</hi> to the number of 600 or 700 men from the <hi>Darty,</hi> encamped them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againe in the former place at our Lieutenants and <hi>Iohn Murrayes</hi> houſes and haggards, falling to their old worke of burning, and ſending a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of our Corne: The next day with a party of Horſe and Foote, we againe fell upon them as before, killing divers of them, their great Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell being ſhot through the hat and through the Pike neare his hand; we brought home to the Caſtle 3 of their ableſt mens heads,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> The wives and boyes of our Souldiers loading themſelves with the burnt Corne and pillage, we burnt thoſe houſes, and what Corne in the haggards we were not able to carry with us, to prevent their further company there, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too farre maſters of the Field.</p>
               <p>Our horſemen ſcouring the Fields apprehended two of the Rogues Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>uary</note> 
                  <hi>Owen Mac Thomas Mac Murray,</hi> and <hi>Ferries Mac Kegan,</hi> two luſty able Rogues, which were the next day hanged.</p>
               <p>Our Colonell being informed that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Parke</hi> at <hi>New-Towne</hi> within 6 miles of our Caſtle,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>uary</note> and 12 miles from <hi>Sligo</hi> was ſtrongly blockt up with a Campe about him in his Caſtle, ſent a party of Horſe and Foote under the command of our Lieutenant, with orders to view their ſtrength, and if poſſible to relieve and ſpeake with Mr. <hi>Parke;</hi> As we marcht to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>New-Towne,</hi> we ſaw little danger, onely ſome ſcouting Rogues from hill to hill. But coming to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Parke,</hi> he tould our Lieutenant that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:96993:12"/>he wiſht us all home againe, holding us all loſt men, as if he had beene ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the plot; Our Lieutenant amazed at his ſpeeches, percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no ſuch ſigne, upon his march admiring M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Parkes</hi> intelligence, finding himſelfe and his Caſtle free, deſired M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Parke,</hi> ſince for his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe our Colonell had ſeut us thither, that he would therefore lend him 20 or 30 of his men for the ſtrengthening of his party homewards, which M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Parke</hi> would by no meanes doe, though perſwaded thereunto by his owne Officers, and divers of his men, who told him it was ſhame for him and them all, he leaving men enough beſides to defend him in his Caſtle, whoſe anſwer was, it was well for him if he could defend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and his till aide come, without Provoking or doing any thing to draw the County upon him: Our Colonell having in perſon upon his intreaty lately viſited him with a ſmall party of Horſe, where ſince it is ſaid, <hi>New-Towne</hi> ſhould have beene the trap to have catcht us all for our kindneſſe to it. On our march homewards we were beſet from all quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters with neere a 1000 men, who within 3 miles to our Colonels Caſtle, gave us a moſt fierce charge in a moſt dangerous rocky place, where our Horſes could make no play, yet did our men ſo bravely behave themſelves being inſtantly ingaged upon puſh of Pike, our Muſquetieres once having given fire in their boſomes, were ſo plyed with their ſtones wherewith they had provided themſelves, and had ſuch dexterity in throwing them, as we got not leave to charge againe; but we falling upon them pell mell with the but ends of our Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets did ſo cloſely ſtand to it, as having by Gods great mercy and power broake through, diſordered and routed them, killing a number, chaſing them like doggs with our Horſe and Foote from hill to hill; In the meane time our Souldies boyes ſtirpped neere 30 of their beſt men of the Counties of <hi>Sligo</hi> and <hi>Leitrim,</hi> of which number was <hi>Mulmurry Mac Ternan</hi> (chiefe of that name) a Juſtice of the Peace who had beene Sheriffe of this County, who with his eldeſt Sonne and heire, and his Sonne in law <hi>Carery ô Trower</hi> chiefe of that name, <hi>Cormack Mac Murray, Farliſſe ô Deganan, Bryan ô Rourke,</hi> and <hi>John ô Crean,</hi> all of them that are named being prime Gentlemen of theſe two Counties, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides a many of their common Souldiers were killed, wherof is made ſmall reckoning amongſt them; It is thought that we cut off that day of all ſorts above threeſcore of them: Our party not conſiſting of 80 Horſe and Foote, of which we loſt in that ſervice only one Pike man and one Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitiere, though many of us were ſore bruiſed with ſtones, and ſleight cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable wounds with puſh of Pike, the Rogues afterwards acknowledging that day they ſaw God was againſt them, they being ten times our num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:96993:13"/>and moſt confident to have deſtroyed us all, yet it pleaſed God thus to preſerve us from this great dammage which we were ingaged in, for that ungrate man Mr. <hi>Parke</hi> his ſake, we brought home with us abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of the Rogues Armes and Apparrell, which was a good ſupply to our Souldiers.</p>
               <p>This day <hi>ô Connour Sligoe</hi> ſhewes himſelfe from that County with his Regiment,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>uary</note> drawing to a Mountaine not much above halfe a mile from our Caſtle.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Connour</hi> with his Regiment encamp'd themſelves in <hi>Cornestacke</hi>-Woods,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ch <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> upon the ſide of a boggie Mountaine not much above halfe a mile from our Caſtle.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Owen ô Rourke</hi> with his Regiment and the aſſiſtance of the County,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ch <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camp'd themſelves on the right-hand of <hi>O Connours</hi> Regiment, in the ſame Woods neare together; <hi>O Connour</hi> ſends a ſeeming friendly Letter by a Boy of 6 or 7 yeares old, adviſing our Colonell to yeeld to ſome Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties with them, and to prevent the eminent ruine was threatned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Caſtle and all in it, which Letter was anſwered with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and diſdaine by our Colonell, who ſcorned any Treaty with Rebels and Traitors.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Owen ô Rourke,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ch <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>O Connour Sligoe,</hi> and all they could then command, being a great multitude, marched towards our Caſtle from their Campe, as if that day they would have done great matters, but having ſhewed themſelves, and marching about us, keeping without Musket-ſhot of our walls, they drew back to their quarters.</p>
               <p>They againe that morning,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ch</hi> 9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> being ſupplied the night before with Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell <hi>Con Mac Donnels</hi> Regiment, which as the day before with neere 2000 men, ſiring ſome Cabbins, and ſheltring themſelves as they ſet fire in the ditches of the Orchard, where of from the Caſtle walls our Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell ſhot two of them with his owne hands, which they carried off retrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to their old quarters.</p>
               <p>Being their Patron S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Patricks</hi> day,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ch <hi>17.</hi>
                  </note> and the day they had prefixed for the deſtruction of our Caſtle and all in it, Our Colonell that morning with Trumpet, Drumme and Colours, marched out with Horſe and Foote towards their unacceſſible Campe with his ſmall number, chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenging them that day to draw neare for performance of their great braggs, where we parlied and made ſome ſport with them a while, a Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and a bogge dividing us; Our Colonell ſending for one of his Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, the Rogues being drawne up in a body right before us, we called to them ſince they durſt not come to performe their promiſe and take the Caſtle, they would reſcue their Country-man who was there to be han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:96993:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>in honour of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Pattrick,</hi> which Priſoner being hanged and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving but an old ſack of ſtraw, long ſtockings being ſowed to it, as it was throwne over the gallowes, our Hang-man ſitting on the gallowes, calling to them if they had charity in them to ſend the poore priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner a Prieſt, they imagining that ſack to be a man, fell all on their knees in our view praying for the Priſoners ſoule.</p>
               <p>Till this day our Campers lay quiet,<note place="margin">April <hi>2</hi>
                  </note> our Colonell daily cauſing the Plough to goe in deſpight of them till this night, that all our plough-Horſes through negligence of our Centries are ſtolne from us, they thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king by that meanes they had overthrowne our ploughing, and the next morning we falling to geere our Ploughes our Colonell cauſeth his Troope-Horſes which had beene kept in the houſe, to be made ready and fall to plowing and ſowing with them faſter then formerly, and ploweth and ſoweth neere foureſcore Barrells of Corne, the Rogues not daring for all their ſtrength to plow or ſow for themſelves within two or three miles of his Caſtle.</p>
               <p>By this time the Rogues grew ſo conſident of their ſecurities in their Campe,<note place="margin">April <hi>7</hi>
                  </note> that the Colonell <hi>ô Rourke</hi> brought his Cattell to graze upon ſome waſt land within two miles of us, wherewith our Colonell being acquainted, that night ſent out a party of Horſe and Foote, and ſeized upon all their Cattell, driving them homewards by breake of day, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they raiſing their Camp, brake out upon us, thinking to have deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us and reſcued their Colonels cattell; but it pleaſed God we ſo paid them, that we not only made good our prey, but killed a number of their ableſt men, bringing with us to the Caſtle, 6 of their chiefe Officers heads, of which number was <hi>James Murrah Mac Glannaghy</hi> the chiefe man of that name, chaſing all the reſt to their Campe, where we found 3 ſtand of Pike-mens Armes, 2 Drummes, 6 Muskets with Bandaliers, 2 Serjeants Halberts, with a many Pikes and Skeanes, moſt of thoſe Armes formerly belonging to the Lord Preſident of <hi>Connaughts</hi> Officers and Souldiers, having layne in Garriſon at <hi>Sligo</hi> till it was loſt and they cut off; Thus we deſtroyed their great Campe, where our Souldiers wives and boyes plentifully victualled themſelves, bringing from the Rogues a many great Iron-crowes and ſuch like inſtruments, made and marked with the ſigne of the Croſſe, making their poore churles beleeve, that with thoſe Irons they were to pull downe our Colonels Caſtle and Bawne.</p>
               <p>A party of Foote was this night ſent to <hi>Glenden,</hi> ſome 5 or 6 miles off,<note place="margin">April <hi>9</hi>
                  </note> where we kil'd and burned in their houſes neere 20 Rogues, bringing home a number of Cowes and Goates, and burning a many of <hi>Iriſh</hi>-houſes.</p>
               <p>Our Colonell this night in perſon,<note place="margin">April <hi>18</hi>
                  </note> marched forth with a party of Horſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:96993:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>and Foote into the County of <hi>Sligo,</hi> where within two miles of the Towne, he burnes of ſome Villages called <hi>Belfather,</hi> and other houſes there, killed ſome Rogues, he returnes by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Parkes</hi> Caſtle of the <hi>New-Towne,</hi> finding that Towne and Caſtle untoucht or troubled, being in the boſome of the Rogues, where our Colonell being informed the Rogues were daily relieved by that Towne and Caſtle, their Cowes having gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed peaceably about the Caſtle all the while their Campe lay about <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour Hamilton,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Parke</hi> never permitting a man of his either to meddle with their cattell or themſelves, as they went and came with their provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions from <hi>Sligo</hi> to their Campe, he having in his Caſtle neare 60 able men, which might have done good ſervice if M. <hi>Parke</hi> and the <hi>ô Rourkes</hi> had not ſo made their bargaines, that untill our Colonels Caſtle were deſtroyed, he ſhould not be medled withall, ſo as he made them no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruption whileſt they were encampt about us; In the meane time M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Parke</hi> cauſing his Weaver to weave 40 yards of broad-cloath for the uſe of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Bryan Ballagh ô Rourke,</hi> whilſt he and his Brother <hi>Owen</hi> were lying in campe about us; And the next day after we had beate them from their campe, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Parke</hi> not only ſuffered them to carry away their cattell, which all that while they grazed neare to his Caſtle gates with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any guard ſave one coward, as alſo that day lent <hi>Bryan Ballagh</hi> the cloath-weaver in his Caſtle, with divers ſuch like informations proved by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Parkes</hi> owne ſervants, whereupon our Colonell thought fit preſently to burne that Towne which ſo long had relieved and ſheltred the Rogues, and killed ſome of them at that inſtant in the Towne.</p>
               <p>Our Horſe men this morning ſcouring the fields,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>il <hi>21.</hi>
                  </note> killed one of the Rogues centryes bringing his head home to the Caſtle.</p>
               <p>This night a party was ſent towards <hi>Dromahere,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 23.</note> where we killed above 40 of the Rogues, burnt many good houſes, brought home 7 or 8 ſcore cowes, with many Horſes, Sheepe and Goates, by this march we diverted another great gathering intended to have encampt about us the next day.</p>
               <p>A party of Foote is ſent into a Wood-land Mountaine countrey 10 mile from our Caſtle,<note place="margin">
                     <hi> May 1.</hi>
                  </note> where by the dawning of the day we fell upon ſome houſes belonging to the great Lord of that Countrey <hi>Mac A Nawe,</hi> where we burnt and killed in the houſes upwards of 3 ſcore perſons, taking <hi>Mac A Nawe</hi> himſelfe, with his two Daughters, and a Kinſ-man Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, his Wife being killed unknowne to the Souldiers, amongſt the reſt we brought home our Priſoners with 8 or 9 ſcore cowes, and neere 200 Sheepe and Goates.</p>
               <p>That night a party of Horſe and Foote are ſent into the countrey of <hi>Sligoe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>May 10.</hi>
                  </note> where we burnt the houſes of <hi>Teig Mac Phelomy ô Connour, Teig
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:96993:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>bog ô Connour,</hi> neere Cozens and Captaines in <hi>O Connours</hi> Regiment, whilſt he lay about us we kil'd ſome 10 or 12 of the Rogues themſelves, being then at <hi>Sligo,</hi> moſt of the people of the <hi>Barrony</hi> being ſled to the Towne for feare of our men; That Country being almoſt waſt, we brought home onely a prey of Sheepe.</p>
               <p>This night we marcht into the County of <hi>Fermannagh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">May <hi>13</hi>
                  </note> where we kild the Wife of <hi>Donnogha Mac Flagherty Mac Gwire,</hi> with about 40 more, whom we ſurpriſed in houſes before day, and brought with us 9 ſcore Cowes, above 200 Sheepe and Goates, and 47 Horſes and Mares, 30 Swine, and 5 Priſoners which we hanged.</p>
               <p>Intending towards the Fryers of <hi>Crewly,</hi> we found that houſe unco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered,<note place="margin">May <hi>18</hi>
                  </note> and the Fryers fled; This morning we encountred a number of <hi>Owen ô Rourkes</hi> men neare to the Caſtle of <hi>Dromahere,</hi> where we killed above 20 of them, our Souldiers got good Pillage in their Cabbins, brought home above an 100, moſt of them <hi>Scotch</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> Cowes, 7 or 8 ſcore Sheepe, ſome luſty Mares and Horſes, with a many Pikes, and the Lord Preſident of <hi>Connaughts</hi> Halbert, his Serjeant being taken when they left <hi>Sligo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This morning our Caſtle is attempted to be taken by 4 or 5 handred Rogues from the <hi>Dartey</hi> or <hi>Roſenver,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">May <hi>20</hi>
                  </note> but our Centries timely giving us the Alarmes, they are reſcued, and the Rogues retyred to the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines.</p>
               <p>In hope this night to meete the Rebels who attempted our Caſtle,<note place="margin">May <hi>21</hi>
                  </note> a party is ſent towards <hi>Glon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an</hi> 6 miles from the Caſtle, where we found a many faire <hi>Iriſh</hi>-houſes, neither man nor beaſt neare them, all which we burnt, and marching homeward we perceived before Sun-riſing a many Rebels at <hi>Largenboy,</hi> within leſſe then a mile to our Caſtle, coming from the County of <hi>Sligo,</hi> with intention that morning to aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ile our Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle: Our party perceiving them, notwithſtanding their ſore chaſe in reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuing the Caſtle the day before, and their hard march that night, yet did we advance towards them with Horſe and Foote within ſpeech of them, our Colonell calling to them from a hill, asked if their errand were for the Caſtle, for the reſcuing their Lord <hi>Mac A Nawe</hi> and his Daughters, or was it Cowes they were ſeeking, they ſhould have a venture for both, our Colonell cauſing a Priſoner to be brought out, told them it was <hi>Mac A Nawe,</hi> to be hanged for their welcome to their ould Campe, which Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner was immediately hanged in their owne view, the gallowes ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding on the top of a hill, within leſſe then two Musket-ſhots, where the Rogues were drawne up, as the Priſoner was throwne over the ladder, we could perceive the Rogues upon their knees, thinking we had hanged
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:96993:15"/>
                  <hi>Mac a Nawe;</hi> After this our Colonell gives order preſently to drive above two hundred milch Cowes towards them, telling them there was the cowes we had lately taken from their deare friend Colonell <hi>Owen ô Rourke,</hi> when they were laſt beaten from their campe, hoping this would have put more mettall in them, ſince they durſt not fight for reſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their friend, they being five times our number, and we unable to reach them as they ſtood on thoſe wooddy boggs, keeping a moſſe and a River betwixt us and them: Whilſt our Colonell parlied with them, his Lady from the caſtle came to us (where we were drawne up over againſt the Rogues) furniſhing us with good ſtore of meate and drinke, which much refreſhed us, having beene upon ſervice two nights together, yet were our ſtomacks ſharper ſet to have beene at the Rogues, then either to meate or ſleepe; but ſeeing the Rogues ſo unwilling to come on, we were commanded on a ſudden to draw towards the caſtle, which the Rogues perceiving fell to ſtripping themſelves, and with a great noyſe and a cry come running towards us, and over the River unto the middle of a moſſe ſcarce Musket ſhot from the caſtle, as if they would have gotten betwixt us and home; which our Colonell perceiving, gives order to the Officers, commanding the Foote to wheele about upon them, which the Rogues no ſooner perceiving, but they preſently fell a running over the River, throwing one another into it; as they croſt, our Musketeeres getting ground of them, gave ſire amongſt the thickeſt of them, killed diveis, hurt many, chaſt the reſt neare 3 miles over Mountaines towards <hi>Sligo,</hi> bringing home their chiefe Commander at that time his head, our Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers being furniſhed with above an 100 of their Mantles, coates and cloakes, 2 Drummes, a many of their Armes, and good ſtore of Meale and other commodities which their Wives and boyes found in their campe, we being tould by 2 Priſoners that all the neghbouring Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties had ſet up their reſts with a reſolution that night to have met, never to have given us over untill they had ſtarved us or taken us out of our ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, but God of his wonted mercy thus diſappointed that damnable plot, without the loſſe of a man to us, to his everlaſting glory and all our comforts.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding our ſeverall ſore marches the Weeke paſt,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ay <hi>22.</hi>
                  </note> we were encouraged by the word of a Priſoner in hope of a ſpeciall peece of ſervice, this night to venture upon a freſh march, where we were conducted neare 14 or 16 miles into the County of <hi>Sligo,</hi> guiding us amongſt moſt dangerous Rocks and glinns, intending to have betrayed us, as afterwards he confeſt; nevertheleſſe it pleaſed God to give us ſuch ſtrength and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and ſent us ſuch a meeting with them, as we killed above 30 in three
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:96993:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>cabbins, brought home a freſh Priſoner, above an 100 cowes, and neere ſo many Sheepe; the crye and Countrey being up in all parts about us, yet never durſt ſo much as venture to reſcue the cattle; At our comming home we hanged our guide, who died a moſt deſperate obdurate villaine.</p>
               <p>A party of Foote was ſent towards <hi>Mounter Kenny,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">May <hi>27</hi>
                  </note> that night we kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led 10 or 12 in their cabbins amongſt the Woods, brought home with us neere 200 cowes an 100 Sheepe, and in our returne we were ſet upon by <hi>Owen ô Rourke,</hi> and the ſonnes of <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c Nawe,</hi> being neere 300 men, where it pleaſed God we not only defended our ſelves and our prey, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo killed and ſtript a many of their beſt men, bringing home a Priſoner with a many of their Armes.</p>
               <p>This night a party of Horſe and Foote are ſent towards ſome Lands of <hi>Owen ô Rourkes</hi> called <hi>Cilkoſh,</hi> where we kided 15 or 16 of his men,<note place="margin">Iune <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> brought home a Priſoner, with ſome few Cowes, Horſes, Sheepe and Goates.</p>
               <p>A party of Foote is ſent towards our Colonels Woods of <hi>Glanſarne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iune <hi>12</hi>
                  </note> where we killed 15 or 16 in thoſe Woods, and brought home 4 Priſoners, with ſome foure-ſcore cowes, and neere ſix-ſcore Sheepe.</p>
               <p>Our Colonell having by vertue of a Commiſſion,<note place="margin">Inne <hi>23</hi>
                  </note> made uſe of ſome 20 of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Parkes</hi> men in proſecution of Rebels, not thinking him to be ſo baſe a Traitour in correſpondency with them as afterwards was proved. This night our Colonell ſends his party with 20 Beeves for the ſupply and relieving <hi>Parke</hi> and his caſtle, with orders that <hi>Parkes</hi> 20 men ſhould returne with our party, there being twice more men with him within his caſtle then was requiſite for the defence thereof: But <hi>Parke</hi> recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Beeves, and getting his 20 men within his caſtle, would not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer a man of them notwithſtanding our Colonels commiſſion and orders to that purpoſe to returne with us.</p>
               <p>Our Colonell much reſenting <hi>Parkes</hi> preſumption the day before,<note place="margin">Iune <hi>24.</hi>
                  </note> this day ſends his Lieutenant with a party of Horſe and Foote, requeſting <hi>Parke</hi> by vertue of our Colonels commiſſion from the Lords Juſtices and Counſell, to draw forth and muſter what ſtrength that caſtle could make, leaving a competent number within it ſelfe for making good the walls; Our Lieutenant orders being that ſo many ſhould be left within the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle as his judgement ſhould thinke fit, and the reſt to march along with our party upon ſome ſpeciall ſpeedy peece of ſervice intended, wherein Sir <hi>William Cole</hi> and his Regiment had ſeverall times denied us aſſiſtance; This motion <hi>Parke</hi> denied to muſter his men untill he perſwaded our Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant to come within his caſtle, where ſhutting the gates, he muſtered neere 60 able men, whereof our Lieutenant demanded 30, which <hi>Parke</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:96993:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>denied, not ſuffering a man of his to come within the caſtle untill ours marcht away.<note place="margin">July <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>This night with Horſe and Foote our Colonell thinkes fit in perſon to viſit M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Parke,</hi> who had ſo beaſtly neglected his Officers in contempt of the Lords Juſtices and Connſells commiſſion, fearing <hi>Parke</hi> was incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning rather to ſubmit himſelfe and his caſtle into the hands of the Rogues whom he held the ſtronger party, and daily correſponded with them, which to prevent, we marcht this night about midnight to his Caſtle walls, requiring <hi>Parke</hi> if he were a ſubject, that upon his Allegiance he would come forth and ſpeake with out Colonell, who after ſome ſhuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſling excuſes and delayes opens his gate, our Colonell commands him ſpeedily to draw forth what men he had within the caſtle, and making choiſe of ſome 20 of them which he joyned to his owne party, cauſed pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to apprehend <hi>Parke</hi> upon ſtrong preſumption of his diſloyalty and his former contempts; Our Colonell preſently puts in an Officer of his owne with the charge of that Caſtle and all in it, which being done, our Colonell marches ſtraight towards the Towne of <hi>Sligo, Parkes</hi> caſtle being within 4 miles of it, none of us that followed him imagining that with ſo ſmall a party he would have anned at ſuch a march, but coming neare to the Towne, our Colonell commanding a halt to be made, and the party to be drawne up in abody, uſing ſome comfortable encouraging ſpeeches, asking if our ſtomacks did ſerve us as his did, to attempt the burning of the Towne now ſo neare it, which maintained ſo many Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious enemies, who had joyned in the burning our poore garriſon, and ſo many times encampt about us and ſought our deſtruction; This motion was no ſooner made by our Colonell then cherefully embraced by us all, ſo recommending our ſelves to his divine mercy, who had many times aſſiſted and delivered us, on we marcht towards the dawning of the day, our Colonell having no other Officers to aſſiſt him in this ſervice, but his Serjeant <hi>Iaviſton,</hi> his Lieutenant and Enſigne being moſt part of this yeare diſeaſed and unſerviceable, our Colonell coming at the Bridge gives orders to the Foote chearefully to follow their Serjeant with what ſilence and ſpeed they were able, and once entring the Towne, no man preſume upon paine of death to enter any honſe for plunder, but with ſire and ſword to deſtroy all we could come at, calling all the ſtreete if any <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Priſoners were amongſt them they ſhould draw to us, as divers did, Our Colonell with his Horſe falling upon a many good houſes full of people on this ſide of the Bridge, where he burned and deſtroyed all, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing his Randevowes with the Foote at the South-weſt end of the Towne, where he croſt a Foard which brought him cloſe to the Friery,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:96993:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>where the foote met and fired their brave maſſe houſe and Fryery, where it is ſaid, we burnt a many good things, which people had given in kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping for ſafety to the Fryars, and all their ſuperſtitious trumperies belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to their Maſſe: It was thought ſome of the Fryers themſelves were likewiſe burnt, two of them running out were killed in their habits: As we finiſhed this worke, and giving God the praiſe for our ſucceſſe, we were tould by ſome Priſoners that <hi>O Connour Sligo</hi> with what ſtrength he could make in that County, was that night marcht to meete <hi>Owen ô Rourke</hi> and the reſt of his old comrades from the County of <hi>Cavan,</hi> for the laying of a new campe about our Colonels caſtle, and the carrying away of our new ſupply of Cowes; upon which newes our Colonell held it fit to haſt homewards, as we marcht hourely expecting to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countred; when we came within 3 miles of our Colonels caſtle, we deſcerned our Colonels Horſe paſſiage ſtrongly to be beſet (being a ſtraight paſſiage) with a number of men, having a Rocky-wood on our right-hand, and a great bogge on the left, ſo that our Horſe-men by our Colonels or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders are forced to try another way, where many of them were bogged their Horſes breaking from them; In the meane-time our Foote-men couragiouſly charged a great body of them neere 300 which were layed for us that way; Thoſe who had beſet our Horſe-paſſages, obſerving our Horſe-men bogg'd, and our Foote engaged with 3 times our number, marcht hard after our Horſe-men, where our Colonell amongſt the reſt was 3 times unhorſt, that day the Rogues playing hard upon him, being well knowne by his Horſe and habit, as ſome of their Priſoners afterwards confeſt; nevertheleſſe, it pleaſed God out of his wonted fatherly mercy, not only to deliver us ſafe out of their hands being a ſmall handfull, not above 7 ſcore Horſe and Foote, who fought our ſelves with neere a 1000 of them from ſeverall quarters, ſtill skirmiſhing with us untill we came neare our Colonels caſtle, our Muskiteeres killing a many of them, with the leſſe only of 3, and ſome few hurt; Notwithſtanding our weariſome march and hot ſervice that night in burning of the Towne of <hi>Sligo,</hi> where it is confeſt by themſelves we deſtroyed that night neere 3 hundred ſoules by fire, ſword and drowning, to Gods everlaſting great honour and glory and our comforts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>James Wetherſom</hi> a <hi>Scotch</hi>-man, married to an <hi>Iriſh</hi>-woman, being at <hi>Sli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iuly <hi>7</hi>
                  </note> and confeſſing, himſelfe to have beene one of <hi>O Connours</hi> Souldiers, was this day hanged.</p>
               <p>A party of Horſe and Foote was this night ſent towards <hi>Killargy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iuly 10.</note> where the Rogues were ſtrongly encampt within 4 miles to our Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels caſtle; we falling on them before day, there we kild and ſtript
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:96993:17"/>above 20 of them, brought home above 8 ſcore of their cowes, were ſet upon by a number of them, who thought to have reſeued the cowes, gave us a moſt deſperate charge, but we kil'd 7 or 8 more of them, and brought home our prey with a many of their Armes, we loſt one of our beſt Muskiteeres in this ſervice.</p>
               <p>Our Colonell being advertized from the County of <hi>Fermanagh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>25.</hi>
                  </note> that Sir <hi>William Cole</hi> had lately taken in upon protection above an 100 <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rogues, allowing them a Captaine of their owne Nation over them, quartering them neare to the way where our meſſengers uſed to paſſe towards <hi>Eniskillen,</hi> which much troubled our Colonell, ſuch a thing ſhould be done by Sir <hi>William Cole</hi> with whom he daily correſponded, without acquainting him with his warrant or reaſons for that act: here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon out Colonell fearing leaſt that ſuch like neighbours ſhould be put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him by Sir <hi>William Cole,</hi> this night ſends a party towards the borders of <hi>Fermanagh,</hi> where a many goodly <hi>Iriſh</hi> houſes with an Iron worke were ſtanding amongſt the Woods, all which our Colonell this night cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be burned; In ſcouring thoſe Woods we found a few cowes and a Priſoners.</p>
               <p>Our Colonell having divers times by Letters advertiſed Sir <hi>William Cole</hi> whileſt the Rogues lay encampt about him,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>26.</hi>
                  </note> deſiring ſome aide from Sit <hi>William</hi> Regiment being moſt part <hi>Scotch</hi>-men, whom our Colonell had adviſed to ſubmit to his command, being of that County which he lived in, yet Sir <hi>William</hi> did never ſince the beginning of theſe troubles, venture ſo much as one meſſenger to ſee what was become of us, for all our Colonell conſtantly twice or thrice a Moneth did adventure meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to him, who was neere 10 times our number: And we being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertized from Sir <hi>William Cole</hi> himſelfe by our meſſengers, that ſome Pouder and Ammunition was ſent from <hi>Dublin</hi> and <hi>London-derry</hi> to <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negall,</hi> for the ſupply of <hi>Eniskillen</hi> and us both, Sir <hi>William</hi> promiſing by his meanes and his ſtronger party, that ſome courſe ſhould be taken for the bringing our Ammunition from <hi>Donegall</hi> as for his owne, which our Colonell relyed upon: yet nevertheleſſe Sir <hi>William</hi> did make that meanes that his owne was brought to <hi>Balliſhannon</hi> within 12 miles to our Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonels caſtle, and unknowne to our Colonell ſends a party of 4 or 5 hundred to <hi>Balliſhannon</hi> for his Ammunition, where he was well ſupplied with Salt, and marched at this time with this party neare to the borders of our Colonels Land, within 6 miles to his caſtle, where our ſmall party might have conveniently met them, and have beene ſupplied as they were, if their intention and wiſhes had beene as neighbourcly towards us, as we were really towards them, who by this and other after carria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:96993:17"/>appeared rather to envy then to pitty our extremities whereof they were fully informed; yet hearing by our laſt meſſenger how God had bleſt and enabled us to doe for our ſelves, and that ſtore of cowes were to be had in our county of <hi>Leytrim,</hi> whereof they heard that we got dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtore: This newes it ſeemes did more invite our neighbour Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then any ſtomack they had to relieve us in our ſeverall diſtreſſes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till this day; A party of neere 400 Horſe and Foote are ſent with Sit <hi>William Coles</hi> Letters to our Colonell, congratulating his ſeverall good ſervices, expreſſing he had now in accompliſhment of our Colonels for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer deſires ſent theſe Gentlemen and Souldiers, to be imployed in ſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the Countrey, and ſuch other ſervices as by our Colonell ſhould be thought fit, without limitation of time or other end mentioned in his Letter; upon reading whereof our Colonell bids their Lieutenant Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell <hi>Acheſon</hi> with the reſt of their Captaines heartily welcome, there being in their company M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Deane Barkeley,</hi> who had marired Sir <hi>William Coles</hi> Daughter, and had lately beene relieved by Sir <hi>William</hi> from the Rogues, in exchange of divers arch-Rebels, Prieſts, Captaines and others of great conſequence; This M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Deane</hi> ſo behaved himſelfe at a conference betwixt our Colonell and their Officers, as if he had come with abſolute power from his Father in law over this party, Officers and Souldiers, their Lieutenant Colonell alledging they were ſent thither by Sir <hi>William Cole</hi> upon information of our meſſenger, that we were blockt up with a ſtrong campe about the Caſtle, and that his orders were to ſtay no longer with out Colonell then the next day, allowing them perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily 48 houres and no longer to be from their Garriſon, they having in that time 40 long miles march through Woods and Mountaines to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, let any man judge what ſervice in the reſt of that time was fit to be ventured on: upon this our COlonell advized them, ſince their private orders were ſuch, contrary to the contents of Sir <hi>Williams</hi> Letters to him, that their beſt courſe was for that night, Commanders and Officer to refreſh themſelves with him in his Caſtle, taking order that their Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers ſhould be quartered and provided for amongſt his Souldiers in their cabbins, which their Officers would not yeeld to, much urging and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portuning our Colonell, that ſince they were come to him, and that they found the Fields cleare about him, as they had beene neere 3 Moneths before that, which they knew well enough whatſoever they pretended; that he ſhould imploy them upon ſome peece of ſervice under his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand before they returned: Our Colonell telling them, God had hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mercifully bleſt his undertakings with his owne handfull, that he was unwilling to engage the honour of what further ſervice he intended up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:96993:18"/>ſuch ſtrict orders, the ſucceſſe and event not fit to be limited with their time; Their Officers ſtill importuning that night to be imployed, whereupon upon their importunities, our Colonell reſolved to try with the aſſiſtance of their ſtrength, the taking of the Caſtle of <hi>Drumahere,</hi> wherein was Colonell <hi>Owen ô Rourke,</hi> with divers of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels of this County, hoping by that ſervice to have relieved Sir <hi>Robert Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney</hi> with his Lady and children, who had beene long Priſoners in that caſtle, thinking Sir <hi>William Coles</hi> men being ſo earneſt, and once en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in the hopes of compaſſing ſo honourable a peece of ſervice, they would not for ſhame have left it, and carried themſelves ſo meanely whilſt we were upon the ſervice as unworthily they did: Our Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell not only in hopes, but full of confidence and probable reaſons, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in perſon with his Horſe and Foote, leading them on neare the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle walls, where he entered his Maſons, Carpenters and other worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men with their inſtruments, who in ſhort time did make a breach, where he placed ſome few Muskiteeres; The Rebels countermanding our work; play ſo hot upon our Muskiteeres as one of them were killed, another deadly ſhot the reſt were beaten from the worke, our Colonels men being wearied out, and having no ſeconding or aſſiſtance from Sir <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Coles</hi> great number, their Lieutenant Colonell having no power to command them to relieve our men, whilſt we were ſpending our lives and bloods in compaſſing this ſervice; <hi>Deane Barkeley</hi> is publikely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging the Officers and Souldiers of Sir <hi>William Coles</hi> party, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them they were not ſent by their Colonell and Governour to take in Caſtles, and that their time limited by their orders was come, wiſhing them at their perils to draw homewards: Our Colonell much grieved and aſhamed to be thus engaged with the hopes of their helpe; adviſed the <hi>Deane</hi> not to meddle with what was out of his Element, deſiring to diſpute the condition of our eſtate with the Lieutenant Colonell and other Officers of the Regiment. The <hi>Deane</hi> replyed the Water was none of his Element, and yet he could ſwimme; and whoſoever ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand that party further, ſhould ſpeake to him. Our Colonell thus diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented, contented, obſerving the unworthy carriage of their Souldiers, who whilſt we were upon ſervice, their Horſe-men were rambling the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, driving in Horſes and Cowes, their Foote-men running after Mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons, catching, killing and waſting under every buſh; Our Colonell en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring after the leſſe of his men to pelſwade them only to lye that night about the Caſtle, knowing by the information of Priſoners, they could not poſſibly have held out 2 dayes, if they had not yeelded that night, as ſince we are informed they intended, and did that night, after
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:96993:18"/>our Colonell marcht from thence, all of them leave the caſtle, leaving Sir <hi>Robert Hanney</hi> with his Lady and children lock't in a roome all alone, till the next day we were not likely to come any more, and that out <hi>Fermannagh</hi> friend had left us in ſuch diſorder, who intended to have carried with them not onely what Cowes and Horſes they had gathered in the fore-mentioned manner whilſt we wore upon ſervice, but alſo thought to have ſtolne with them divers of our Colonells cattell that morning they wero to part; wherewith our Colonell being acquainted, perceived that their intended kindneſſe and viſit to him, was only to have made uſe of his perſon and ſtrength to have prey'd our Countrey for them, which he held no ſitting imployment for his perſonall ſervice, conſidering how unworthily they had carried themſelves towards him in the time of our diſtreſſe, and particularly in this laft ſervice; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon order was given by our Colonell, that not only his owne, cattell ſhould be reſcued from them, but what elſe they had taken whilſt he was in the Fields, telling their Captaines it was ſhame for them, they being 6 times our number, to offer to take any thing from us, ſince they have made us the worſe and not the better for them: This much vexed <hi>Deane Barkeley,</hi> who pretended a Horſe to be taken from him, which he had catch't himſelfe whilſt we were upon ſervice about the caſtle, our Colonell telling him, ſince he had deſerved no better amongſt us, he ſhould carry no Horſe from thence to bragge of; wiſhing the beſt 2 Horſes on his ſtable, with 500 punds in money had beene ſent his Father in law and himſelfe to <hi>Eniskillen,</hi> ſo that the Deane had not come to this march, who carried himſelfe more like a Devill then a Deane: For the. Captaines and Officers being aſhamed of themſelves, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving our Souldiers to be but a few, and daily imployed, were perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by our Colonell for his Majeſties ſervice, and as a ſmall ſupply for the ſafety of our caſtle and Garriſon, to lend our Colonell for ſome time 5 men out of every one of their Companies, making up 30 men to him, and having received theſe men from the ſeverall Captaines, our Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant is commanded by the Colonell for the better grace and credit of their party, to march a part of their way with our Horſe and Foote, and as our Lieutenant and they were a parting, <hi>Deane 'Barkley</hi> had like to have raiſed a mutiny, and have ſet their party and ours by the eares, threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thoſe men left with their Colonell by the Captaines conſents, ſo as halfe of them at that inſtant preſently ranne away from us with this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy carriage of Sir <hi>William Coles</hi> party by the Deane of <hi>Cloghers,</hi> meanes. Our Colonell acquaints Sir <hi>William Cole</hi> by a Letter, hoping he would have reſented his Sonne in lawes arrogant and preſuptuous
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:96993:19"/>carriage, and have ſent us ſome ſupply of more men, but farre other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then we expected, Sir <hi>William</hi> in his anſwer, rather juſtified his Sonne in lawes actions, condemning and cenſuring his Captaines for the few men they had lent our Colonell, denying the former, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging in this Letter for what he ſent his party, deſiring that thoſe few men which had not runne away with the reſt by his Sonne in lawes threatnings, ſhould be ſpeedily returned him, and accordingly they were: And after this unworthy uſage of Sir <hi>William Cole,</hi> our Colonels Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier obſerving the liberty and diſorderly governement and diſcipline of thoſe <hi>Eniskillen</hi> Souldiers, begun daily to runne away to <hi>Eniskillon,</hi> where they found ſhelter and imployment amongſt their Captaines, to the great diſcomfort of our Colonell, and the hazard of us all.</p>
               <p>A party of Foote is ſent to the County of <hi>Cavan,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>guſt <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> where we kil'd above 20 Rogues, bringing home 2 Priſoners, and 7 or 8 ſcore cowes, and above 200 Sheepe and Goates.</p>
               <p>A party is ſent towards <hi>Ballyſhannon</hi> in the County of <hi>Donegall,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>guſt <hi>22</hi>
                  </note> where we kil'd 17 Rogues, and burned many houſes in that Countrey, and brought home a few cowes.</p>
               <p>Our Colonell being advertized that ſome 2 miles on this ſide <hi>Sligo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>guſt <hi>25</hi>
                  </note> a guard of Horſe-men did daily come forth with their Reapers of corne, and hoping to meete with them, this night a party of Horſe and Foote was ſent with ſome guides to lye in ambuſh for them, where having layne till noone, none appearing, that day our orders were to burne and prey what we could in that countrey, where we burned of ſeverall Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liages, as <hi>Donoly, Formorley, Collrey</hi> and <hi>Liſduff,</hi> with a many other ſtrag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling houſes in the countrey, where we met with 3 or 4 ſcore cowes, and above an 100 Sheepe. By this time the countrey gathers, thinking to have reſcued our prey and have beaten us, but it pleaſed the Lord ſo in his wonted mercy to ſtand for us, as that day we kil'd above 40 of their beſt men, ſtript them all, brought home a Priſoner, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relieved the caſtle of the <hi>New-Towne</hi> with a ſhare of our cowes and Sheepe, divers of their beſt Gentry, the <hi>ô Connours,</hi> and the <hi>ô Harts</hi> being thus killed; We marcht Horſe and Foote towards the <hi>Roſſe</hi> in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Sligo,</hi> whence we brought a prey of neere 6 or 7 ſcore cowes, and above 300 Sheepe and Goates, where in our retreat we were ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the greateſt ſtrength of the county, who were gotten into a great head to the Towne of <hi>Sligo,</hi> with intention that day to have layed a new C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>npe about our Caſtle, which this encounter diverted, we killing as was afterwards acknowledged by Priſoners neere 60 of their ableſt men, with two of their famous Prieſts, <hi>Connour ô Hart,</hi> and <hi>Donnell ô Lynch,</hi>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:96993:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>bringing home 7 Priſoners, 5 whereof were hanged the next day, one of them called Captaine <hi>Conô Connour</hi> and the other <hi>Cormack ô Hoy</hi> who had beene a Miniſter amongſt our Colonels Pariſhes, who ſince this Rebellion profeſſed much loyalty, though a kindly traitour, his Father being Viccar generall in the county of <hi>Sligo,</hi> was ſom: yeares agoe quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered in the Towne of <hi>Sligo</hi> for treaſonable ſpeeches againſt the King and State.</p>
               <p>The Colonell this day heares divers ſhot of Ordinance towards <hi>Sligo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Septem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> which put him in ſome hopes of ſome Army towards that place, or reliefe towards us.</p>
               <p>This night a party of Horſe and Foote was ſent towards the Sea-coaſt to ſearch for a Priſoner,<note place="margin">Septem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> for intelligence what ſhooting it was we heard the day before, where we fell on, there the countrey gathered together to oppoſe the landing of men, where 2 Ships lay within the harbour of <hi>Sligo;</hi> we gave the Rogues the Alarme, who fled all to a ſtrength of an old Caſtle neare the Sea-coaſt, we brought home one Priſoner, of whom we learned that ſome of the <hi>O Donnells</hi> and <hi>O Galloghers</hi> from <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter</hi> were joyned with the county of <hi>Sligo</hi> Rebels to the number of 4 or 500 thinking thoſe Ships carried men, Moncy, Victuals and Ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for out relieſe, but it ſeemed their greater errand thither, was to ſee for a Barque which the Merchants of <hi>Sligo</hi> had loaded with ſeverall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities with corne and cattell from the <hi>Oyſter-Iſland,</hi> where they landed ſome men, and burned divers houſes, going to Sea afterwards, and as yet unknowne to us what they were.</p>
               <p>This night we marcht againe into the County of <hi>Sligo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">September <hi>27.</hi>
                  </note> where within a little more then a mile to that Towne, we burnt a great village, <hi>Ennagh</hi> belonging to <hi>Andrew Crean</hi> the late Sheriffs of that County, we kild a number of Corne-reapers, and brought with us a Priſoner.</p>
               <p>By reaſon of our daily ſervice,<note place="margin">October <hi>2</hi>
                  </note> never any wayes ſupplied or relieved now almoſt a yeare ſince the Rebellion begunne, our Colonell in this extremity, thinkes fit this night to ſend the moſt part of his men towards <hi>Eniskillen,</hi> for ſome Armes and Ammunition which was ſent thither by the conveniency of Sir <hi>Robert Stewarts,</hi> guarding the <hi>Eniskillen</hi> party from the <hi>Derry,</hi> wherewith Sir <hi>Robert</hi> worthily and lovingly adverti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed our Colonell from <hi>Eniskillen</hi> with what was left for him there with Sir <hi>William Cole,</hi> who had promiſed to give his beſt aſſiſtance for the ſpeedy conveying and guarding of thoſe neceſſaries to us: But our party coming to <hi>Eniskillen,</hi> relying upon the aſſiſtance of Sir <hi>William Coles</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment, not only for the guarding of our Armes and Ammunition, but
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:96993:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>alſo for the reſtoring and returning our runne-awayes which had beene unlawfully ſheltered and employed amongſt them. Our Officer deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a guard for both thoſe purpoſes, is offered the Armes and Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition if without a guard we would venture on them, our runne-awayes are ſo concealed and diſperſed amongſt them, as no helpe is made for us for them at all where there were 14 or 15 of them, Sir <hi>William Cole</hi> never appearing amongſt us, but his gates ſhut againſt us, and his bridge drawne up as if we had beene Rebels come to take in his Caſtle, not offering us or our Officers ſo much as one bit of Bread, or cup of ſmall Beere in his Caſtle or Garriſon, our Colonell having formerly enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained 500 of his plentifully two nights though they wronged him; Thus not daring without a guard to venture upon the Kings Armes and Ammunition with ſo weake a party ſo farre a march through Woods and Mountaines, we were forced with no ſmall hazard to make what ſpeede we could from whence we came; Our Colonell being advertized before our coming that the Countrey was ſtrongly gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to have layed for us in our coming home, but we miſſed of our errand.</p>
               <p>Moſt of this Weeke was imployed by us Men, Women and Boyes, in fetching in of Corne from the Rebels, from the bordering counties of <hi>Sligo</hi> and <hi>Fermannagh,</hi> with what was neare us in our own countrey, whereof it pleaſed God we had a good ſupply without the leſſe of a man, woman or child, though daily threatned with great bravadoes, yet they durſt not cut any graine for themſelves ſcarce on this ſide <hi>Sligo</hi> bridge, where abundance of Wheate, Rye and Barley rotted upon the ground for want of meanes and helpe for us to bring it from thence, which <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannagh</hi> men might conveniently have done both for their owne ſupply and ours.</p>
               <p>Seven of our Colonels men left at <hi>New-Towne</hi> for a guard within 4 miles of <hi>Sligo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ctober <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> upon little Naggs chardged 50 or 60 reaping Corne neare <hi>Sligo,</hi> where they killed 4 of them, chaſed the reſt, brought home a Priſoner, with 18 or 20 Horſes and Carrs the Rogues had beene draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing corne withall; The Priſoner being brought to our Colonell, informes him that 2 Congans of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter</hi> Rogues, under the command of Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Manus Mac Egnahan ô Donnell,</hi> and Captaine <hi>Ferdinando ô Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logher</hi> were joyned with Captaine <hi>Teig Mac Phelomy ô Connour,</hi> who lay at a Towne of <hi>ô Connors</hi> called <hi>Broad Culline,</hi> ſome 12 miles from us, with intention ſhortly to have a ſling at our Caſtle.</p>
               <p>Upon this intelligence,<note place="margin">October <hi>21.</hi>
                  </note> our Colonell thinkes fit this night to ſend a party of Horſe and Foote to prevent theſe Gentlemens viſit, where we
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:96993:20"/>met with them in the place our Priſoner informed us, having good ſport with them for a while in killing neere 60 of them with all their 3 Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, &amp; Captain <hi>Teig ô Connours</hi> Wife, his Brother having been formerly a Captaine, and brought hither Priſoner was hanged, we brought home this day neere 200 cowes with a Priſoner, burning the Towne of <hi>Broad Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line</hi> belonging to <hi>ô Connour,</hi> with divers other ſmall Villiages neare it.</p>
               <p>Our Colonell in expectation Sir <hi>William Cole</hi> and his Captaines would now have uſed ſome meanes to have guarded his Armes,<note place="margin">Octob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>1</hi>
                  </note> Ammunition and runne-awayes, as partly they promiſed within a weeke or 10 dayes of our laſt being with them, whereof ſeeing no performance, and our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſtore in that kind, as alſo our ſalt being almoſt quite ſpent, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding that Sir <hi>William Cole</hi> had lately beene ſupplied from <hi>Balli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhannon:</hi> In this extremity moſt of our company is againe commanded in a party to <hi>Eniskillen,</hi> with Letters to Sir <hi>William Cole</hi> mentioning our extremities, ſending money by our Lieutenant for what ſalt could be had at any rate, either for love or money, which orders of Sir <hi>William</hi> inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded no better to us then in our laſt march to that purpoſe, that we ſhould our ſelves venture upon the Armes and Ammunition, we were at a ſtand every way, and leaving it to God and better times, to judge and revenge our uſage upon theſe laſt Letters, our Armes and Ammunition are deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered us with a Letter to our Colonell, but no guard nor ſupply of ſalt to be had; Thus it pleaſed God to bring us ſafe home with what we recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, ſtill deteyning our run-awayes, making uſe of them.</p>
               <p>Our Souldiers being weary after their ſore march for our Ammunition,<note place="margin">Novem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> the weather being faire, all the Women and Boyes are ſent towards <hi>Dro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mahere</hi> to looke for corne, where with a ſmall guard of Horſe and ſome fire-locks, they marched where they met with ſtore of corne, coming all loaden home in ſpight of many Rogues that appeared to them upon ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall hills.</p>
               <p>We are this day likely to be ſurprized by neere a 1000 Rogues from the counties of <hi>Fermannagh</hi> and <hi>Cavan,</hi> under the command of Serjeant Major <hi>Hugh Mac Bryan Mac Gwire;</hi> thinking to have carried away all our cattell, preſuming on their multitudes againſt our handfull, which they thought had not recovered their laſt ſore march from <hi>Eniskillen,</hi> and having layen in ambuſh all night, expecting the drawing out of our cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell in the morning; but finding themſelves diſcovered by 2 of our Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men who ſcoured the Fields before our cattell, theſe two men were ſo engaged amongſt the Rogues that they were both killed, we taking the Alarme, reſcued our Cattell, where we had a ſound encounter with the Rogues, who vvere neere 10 times our number, thinking to have ſvval<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:96993:21"/>us up; they giving the beſt fire, and coming the fiercelieſt for one charge, of moſt that we met withall this yeare: but after charge we did pepper them both with Horſe and Foote, as that they made both aſpeedy and diſorderly retreat, we breaking the legge of the only beſt Souldier and Captaine amongſt them called <hi>Charles Mac Gwier</hi> who had long ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and led on ſome 4 ſcore of their Musketeeres moſt deſperately, and for his good ſervice our Colonell to cure him, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to be carried on a barrow to the gallowes, where he rayled at us all for that he could not obtaine a Souldiers death, to be ſhot at a poſt, having formerly beene twice ranſomed in two Kings ſervices, <hi>Spaine</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> and this morning commanding 300 proper men, not thinking that night to dye like a Dogge on <hi>Mannour Hamiltons</hi> gallowes, ſaying, he obſerved now God was againſt them, acknowledging themſelves to be 10 times our number, and that it was the Devill brought him from his former honourable ſervice to this baſe and miſerable end. In this dayes ſervice, we killed divers of the beſt men of both Counties, brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging home the heads of <hi>Shane Roe Mac Gwire,</hi> which Col: <hi>Conaught Mac Flagherty Mac Huc,</hi> ſonne in law to <hi>Mac A Nawe</hi> who had beene long our Colonels Priſoner till this day, he was hanged for company with the Captaine and his ſonne in lawes kind viſit to him: We brought home Priſoners, <hi>Phelomy Mac Peirce Mac Gwire,</hi> who had beene Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeant to the Serjeant Majors company, who ſcaped very narrowly, him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe being enforced to quit his Horſe, and to goe away ſore wounded by the benefit of a boggie Wood neere by him. Thus it pleaſed God to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able us to deale with theſe Rogues.</p>
               <p>A party is ſent towards the borders of <hi>Monter Kenny,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ember</note> where we killed 14 or 15 Rogues, burnt a many of houſes, brought home a Priſoner with neere a 100 cowes.</p>
               <p>Being in great diſtreſſe and want of Salt,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ember</note> Sir <hi>William Cole</hi> having uſed us as before is mentioned, our Colonell reſolves this night to adventure a party towards <hi>Balliſhannon</hi> in hope there to be ſupplied: Our party marching in the night-time, is by the Rogues centryes diſcovered: Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe we marcht freely to <hi>Balliſhannon</hi> before day, where Captaine <hi>Folliot</hi> hearing our Colonels trumpet and our Lieutenant, ſends out the Boate for our Lieutenant, who delivering our Colonels Letter, deſiring to be ſupplied with ſome ſalt, Captaine <hi>Folliot</hi> wiſhing he had ſooner known our Colonels wants either of ſalt or Ammunition, there being 2 Barrels of Pouder with Match and Lead proportionable ſent from <hi>Derry</hi> to <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negall</hi> for our Colonels uſe, with the like proportion for Sir <hi>William Cole,</hi> who acquainted our Colonell therewith by his Letter, promiſing the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:96993:21"/>like care ſhould be taken by him for bringing our Ammunition from <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negall</hi> as of his owne, which Captaine <hi>Folliot</hi> ſaid might as well, as eaſily have beene done if Sir <hi>William Cole</hi> had but writ ſo much to him, when by <hi>Folliots</hi> meanes his was brought to <hi>Balliſhannon,</hi> from thence by Sir <hi>William Coles</hi> party to <hi>Eniskillen;</hi> In which march they came within 6 miles of our Colonels caſtle, ſo it is eaſie to be judged what comfortable neighbourhood or aſſiſtance, either for his Majeſties ſervice or our ſafety we have had from <hi>Eniskillen:</hi> After diſputing this particular with Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Felliot</hi> he ſhewes our Lieutenant what ſalt Sir <hi>William Cole</hi> had left him, being not above 4 Barrels, whereof he ſent our Colonell two, who expected 20, ſending money and Horſes to that purpoſe with our party<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by this occaſion we brought with us for our Ladies uſe a good woman called <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nye Hale;</hi> As we marched homewards, we could perceive as we came within 6 miles to our Garriſon, the fields fowle on all quarters, which ſet us the better upon our guard, not daring to diſperſe our ſelves in gathering of Cattell which we obſerved to be driven in our wayes, thinking to have tempted us for the greater advantage againſt us, we ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving gotten neere 3 ſcore which we drave before us till we came neare the borders of our Colonels land, where on a ſuddaine we were engaged amongſt the Regues, who had laid a ſtrong ambuſh for us being within little more then puſh of Pike before we could perceive them, ſo as we were preſently engaged to puſh of Pike before our Muskiteeres could give fire, which afterwads they did over our Pike-mens ſhoulders, the Rogues ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingmoſt deſperately to it for almoſt half an houre, they being a pickt party of the beſt and ableſt men that were of the borders of <hi>Fermanagh</hi> and <hi>Ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trim,</hi> moſt of them <hi>O Flannigans, Mac Gwires</hi> and <hi>Mac Caffries,</hi> from the Barrony of <hi>Towro,</hi> with the <hi>Mac Glannaghies, Mac Glanghlins ô Freiles,</hi> and <hi>ô Meaghens</hi> of the <hi>Dartrye,</hi> and <hi>Roſſonter,</hi> whereof we kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led neere 3 ſcore of their propereſt and beſt men, with their chiefe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander, who had beene a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Souldier, called <hi>Bryan Durrogh ô Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey,</hi> with divers others of their Gentlemen whom our boyes ſtript, bringing home a number of their cloathes and Armes; This glorious victory broke the hearts of the moſt daring dangerous men of both thoſe Counties, to Gods holy name be the praiſe and honour, who thus mercifully deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered us without the loſſe of a man, though a many hurt with puſh of Pike and darts; The ſervice was performed upon S. <hi>Andrewes</hi> day, for the credit of our <hi>Scottiſh</hi>-Patron.</p>
               <p>A party is ſent to ſcoure the Woods of <hi>Roſſender,</hi> and to ſearch for corne,<note place="margin">Dece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> whence we brought above an 100 Cowes, our women and boyes being well loaden with good ſtore of burnt corne, where we kild 3 Rogues and brought home a priſoner.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:96993:22"/>
               <p>This night our Colonell intends a party of his Chriſtians to be kept at <hi>Ballymote,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>mber</note> where he hopes to burne of that Towne, not doubting by Gods former favour and mercy the performance thereof, had not a many of his Souliers beene ſeduced to a moſt damnable plot, to have runne away to Sir <hi>William Cole,</hi> being incouraged thereto by the report of a meſſenger our Colonell had lately come from thence, informing what liberty his Souldiers had there, who would not be commanded by Captaine or Officer, which damnable plot had ſo taken amongſt a many of the party, that being marched but a ſmall way, they pretend ſuch faintneſſe and wearineſſe, that the like was never obſerved amongſt them; not knowing what the miſtery could meane, our Lieutenant is found contrary to his orders to march back againe, by this meanes was this ſervice overthrowne, for which our Colonell thankes <hi>Eniskillen,</hi> on which retreat we encountred ſome Rogues, whereof we kil'd 6 or 7, and brought home neere 3 ſecre Cowes, which were no very welcome preſent to our Colonell, in compariſon of what ſervice that night he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to have beene done: This party no ſooner came home, but our Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell diſcovered the whole plot, where he tooke ſuch courſe with them as he found the whole cauſe proceeded from <hi>Eniskillen,</hi> and the countenance was given his run-awayes there.</p>
               <p>A party is ſent towards <hi>Clanlogh</hi> on the borders of <hi>Mounter Kenny,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> where we kil'd divers Rogues, bringing home 2 Priſoners, above 200 Cowes, burnt a many houſes in the Countrey, our women and boyes to a great number coming home loaded with ſtore of burnt Corne.</p>
               <p>We marcht into the County of <hi>Cavan,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> where in the <hi>Laragane</hi> we burnt ſome houſes, kil'd ſome few Rogues, brought home a priſoner, and neere 9 ſcore Cowes.</p>
               <p>We were guided by a Priſoner to the County of <hi>Cavan,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> where on our march through <hi>Glanſarne,</hi> we apprehended a moſt Arch-rogue, called <hi>Cormack ô Quillan,</hi> who had all that yeere ſtolne a many of our Colonels Horſes; from the County of <hi>Cavan</hi> we brought this night neere 200 very faire Cowes, moſt of them as fat as if it had beene at <hi>Michaelmas;</hi> Thus we retreated through <hi>Glanſerne,</hi> killing ſome 5 Rogues, our women and boyes being loaded with Corne.</p>
               <p>We marcht towards <hi>Mounter Kenny,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> where this night we kil'd ſome Rogues, tooke Priſoner the Wife of <hi>Owen oge Mac Murray,</hi> the chiefe man of that name, himſelfe ſcaping narrowly, we brought home 3 ſcore Beeves a many of them very fat.</p>
               <p>We marcht towards <hi>Dromahere,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 17.</note> hearing a great gathering was there making ready for a new Campe againſt us, where on our march through
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:96993:22"/>a Wood within leſſe then a mile to <hi>Dromahere,</hi> where their new Campe lay over againſt it at <hi>Crewly,</hi> we brought from thoſe Woods ſome 3 or 4 ſcore principall Beeves, killed ſome Rogues, and brought home 2 Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, returning one of them being a wench of ſome 10 or 12 yeares old with a Letter of our Colonels <hi>Iriſh</hi>-Souldiers to their Countrymen in Campe, neare the Abbey of <hi>Crewley,</hi> the coppy of which Letter here fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>To the moſt unworthy cowardly Colonels, Captaines, and ſuch like ragged Regiment now gazing for our Colonels <hi>Easter</hi> Proviſion neare <hi>Dromahere</hi> and <hi>Crewley.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>MOst diſloyall, diſhonourable and unworthy Countrymen, we are much aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of your baſe cowardlineſſe, that makes us ſo long expect your threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to ſteale away our Colonels Cowes. If you had followed the counſell of that perjured dastard <hi>Owen Mac a Bryan</hi> you had made more haſt, who thought it time to runne away himſelfe after we found him in a buſh, whilſt we were upon ſervice againſt the Rogues your friends of <hi>Fermannagh,</hi> but if you make no great haſt, our Cowes are few enough to eate till thoſe be fat you now Herd for us neare <hi>Cromahere,</hi> where you lye deſtroying your owne poore Churles, and deviſing lyes to keepe them in heart, your ſelves keeping the Caſtle untill wee rouſe you up as we did the laſt morning, whilst wee gave you a viſit looking for our breake faſt. Tell <hi>Teig</hi> and <hi>Turlogh Mac A Nawe</hi> with their Nephew <hi>Hugh</hi> that would be <hi>ô Rourke,</hi> that their Sister his neece feares there to Beeve in the Lent time, is like to bring their two Siſters to their Father, and when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they came within ſight of his Caſtle, where the ſigne ſteale <hi>Mac A Nawe</hi> two Daughters upon <hi>Mannour Hamiltons</hi> Gallowes, which worſhip may be timely challenged by the Brothers and Gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>d-child. Commend us to that Low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie Lords Sonne <hi>Luke Taffe,</hi> and <hi>Bryan Mac Donnoghy</hi> his baſe Brother in law, who the laſt yeare loſt their owne County, to helpe to ſteale our Colonels Cowes, which many a luſty lad and poore Churle with their Cowes and Sheepe of that County hath well paid for ſince, though they be wiſe enough to keepe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from danger untill their turne come to doe ſacrifice to our Gallowes, which hath well flouriſhed ſince they were here with their friends and Country-men in hope to doe themſelves ſervice at laſt; The Country cry out they will complaine to <hi>Owen Roe ô Neale</hi> for your careleſſe blowing away your Pouder, bleſt and ſent by the Pope to other purpoſe then to ſhoote at our Colonels Castle from the top of <hi>Benbowe,</hi> thinking your braggs will carry it here as in other places, where you are not ſo well tryed or knowne; So wiſhing your ſpeedy converſion
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:96993:23"/>which is downefall, but rather confuſion, who have beene the actors and instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in this abhominable, barbarous and deteſtable Rebellion, adviſing your poore ignorant Country-men churles, to forſake longer following ſuch lying and ſeducing leaders, and truſt to our meanes for ever, ſo once more fare-well-and be hanged,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>You loyall diſaffected Country-men</hi>
                           <list>
                              <item>Shane Roe Mac Roy,</item>
                              <item>Hugh ô Fellan,</item>
                              <item>Cormack ô Clery,</item>
                              <item>Edmond ô Kelly,</item>
                              <item>Bryan ô Fellan,</item>
                              <item>Conner ô Fynny,</item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Cum ceteris in</hi> Culnia.</item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Caſtle Hamilton</hi> 
                           <date>this <hi>17</hi> of <hi>February, 1643.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>THis day being Wedneſday before <hi>Eaſter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rch <hi>29.</hi>
                  </note> having ſent no party abroad ſince the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of <hi>Feb:</hi> in expectation of Sir <hi>William Coles</hi> men from <hi>Eniskillen,</hi> who our Colonell was informed were in great diſtreſſe there, both for Corne and Cattell, neither being to be had for venturing in that County, wherefore our Colonell advertiſed Sir <hi>William Cole</hi> and his Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, that here was faire hopes to be ſupplied, if they would with their party of 4 or 500 men, ſecretly haſt to us, who ſhould be ready to joyne with them for falling upon the Rogues campe, who lay neare and about the Caſtle of <hi>Dremahere,</hi> 6 miles from us, where the Rogues were plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully provided in the Campe, both from the County of <hi>Sligo</hi> and this County, having above 7 or 8000 Cowes about this time grazing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them, and that countrey full of Corne, whereof both <hi>Eniskillen</hi> and we at this time ſtand in great need. The Captaines of <hi>Eniskillen</hi> in their anſwer, acknowledge the extremity of their wants and our Colonels in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitation, but are in ſuch confuſion and diſorder amongſt themſelves, as they neither denied to come or promiſe any thing plainely, when we deferring, all this while unwilling to feare their Campe, or venture our handfull againſt 10 or 12 Companies commanded by Colonell <hi>Lucas Taffe,</hi> and his Lieutenant Colonell <hi>Bryan Mac Donnoghye,</hi> with the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Colonell <hi>Owen ô Rourke,</hi> who lyes in the Caſtle of <hi>Drom here,</hi> but now ſeeing no appearance of <hi>Eniskillen</hi> men, and our owne Cowes and proviſion growne very ſhort againſt <hi>Eaſter,</hi> our Colonell is neceſſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to venture with his owne ſmall party, which adventure it pleaſed the Lord this day ſo to bleſſe, as to enable us to bring from the very Caſtle walls of <hi>Dromahere</hi> neere 400 Cowes, with pretty ſtore of Sheeps, Goates and Mares, with ſome ſmall ſupply of Butter and Meale, fighting our ſelvs through a great body of the Rogues, where we kild divers, hurt above 40, as appeares by one of their Officers Letters found in their Lieutenant Col: pocket, being kild by us 3 dayes after, chaſt the reſt into Woods and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:96993:23"/>boggs, bringing home our prey, and 3 Priſoners without the loſſe of a man, one Muskiteere only hurt on the ſhoulder, ſo that if <hi>Eniskillen</hi> men had beene adviſed by our Colonell, we had undoubtedly had a faire pull of at leaſt 7 or 8000 Cowes, with abundance of Wheate and other corne beſides: what good ſervice might have beene done upon the Rogues, how they can anſwer the neglect of this and other ſuch like ſervice, whereunto they have ſeverall times beene invited and advertized by our Colonell, both for his Majeſties ſervice, the common good, and their owne partcular relife, as more clearely it ſhall appeare hereafter, God ſending us aide and indifferent Judges to heare us both.</p>
               <p>Being <hi>Eaſter</hi>-eve,<note place="margin">April <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> our Hay for Horſes growing ſhort by reaſon of the number we and our Colonell kept within the Caſtle all Winter, he is forced to venture 24 of his trowſe Geraldmes to graze neare 2 miles from the Caſtles, with a guard of neere 50 of his men to take charge of his Plow-horſes and his Cowes, hoping till after Eaſter the Rogues being ſo lately beaten by us, they would not have ventured, as this day they did, a great body of them appeare within a ſhort mile to our Caſtle, before our Centries deſcried them; We taking the Alarme, moſt of our beſt Horſe and beſt Pike-men being ſo farre from us, divers others of our Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers being imployed about fire-wood and ſuch like neceſſaires, ſo as we are not able in this extremity to make up above 50 fighting men, if ſo many, with which number we were commanded to endeavour the reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuing of the reſt, guarding our Horſes and Cattell, having no other way or meanes to ſave all or looſe all; where it pleaſed the Lord ſo to direct us boldly to march towards the Rogues as they were advancing towards our Geldings and Cattell, perceiving our ſmall number ſtraglingly draw together, they with ſpeed advance towards us, marching in 3 diviſions, their firſt diviſion being led-on by their Lieutenant Colonell <hi>Bryan Mac Donnoghy,</hi> and on the head of his owne Company Captaine <hi>Francis Taffe,</hi> and Captaine <hi>Cormaok ô Hawes</hi> Company, which diviſion conſiſts of 44 Muskiteeres beſides Pike-men, the ſecond diviſion is led only by their Serjeant Major <hi>Teigreagh ô Dowde;</hi> In the head of his owne Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany Captaine <hi>David ô Dowde,</hi> and Captaine <hi>Bryan ô Hares</hi> Company conſiſting of 42 Muskiteeres; The third diviſion lead-on by Captaine <hi>William Tyrrell,</hi> on the head of his owne Company Captaine <hi>Bryan Mac Swyne,</hi> and Captaine <hi>Roger ô Conners</hi> Company Conſiſting of 45 Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiteeres beſides Pike-men, which multitude thinking to have ſwallowed up our handfull, perceiving us draw up without Horſe-men, thinking to cut thoſe off before we joyne with the reſt, their Lieutenant Colonell leading on moſt fariouſly along a Bridge, over a River, at the foote of the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:96993:24"/>hill where our men were drawne up, we perceiving them all croſſe the River, marching in a looſe body towards us, giving fire upon us, we ſeeme a little to retreat, where we got the benefit of a ditch for all our Muskiteeres to play out of, whereupon the Rogues imagining we had taken the retreat, did with great ſhoutes crye out as if they had already beaten us; but our Muskiteeres did from that ditch ſo pepper them, that it is not to be beleeved what a ſudden alteration our handfull made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt their multitude, our Pike-men flying in upon them, where one M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>John Connigham</hi> himſelfe was deadly ſhot with a Mukit bullet in the body, who lived 2 dayes after; Thus having kil'd their Lieutenant Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell, who fought moſt deſperately as ever man did, divers being with ſhot and Pike beaten to the ground, yet did he fight upon his knees, pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſo great courage ſhould have beene in ſo Arch a Traitour, who was thought, to have beene one of the greateſt fire-brands of <hi>Connaght</hi> in this Rebellion, and the bloudieſt tyrant aganiſt our Clergy-men, having cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed 3 of them to be murthered, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Thowas Fullerton,</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>William Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stowne,</hi> and <hi>Pattrick Dromond,</hi> who were bloudily kil'd by his orders, when they firſt lay about this Caſtle; Yet bleſſed be God this day who enabled us ſo to deale with them, as we put the Rogues after killing their Lieutenant Colonell, to ſuch a diſorderly and confuſed retreat over the River, where numbers of them threw one another into it, ſo as it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt incredible to ſpeake or write what number of proper perſonable men as any <hi>Ireland</hi> affords, were kil'd that day by our weake handfull, to God alone be the glory. The next day our Colonell ſending forth to ſearch the Fields, to ſee if the Rogues had dar'd in the night time to carry off any of their dead bodies, but it did not appeare they durſt meddle with any; whereupon order was given for burying of them all, which was 2 dayes labour for 20 men, there being neere 3 ſcore found and buried, beſides divers which had beene carried away by the River, there being then a great ſlood in it. Thus it pleaſed God to continue his former fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours and mercy towards us, with this great and miraculous victory with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the loſſe of a man of ours, other then M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Conningham,</hi> our Women and Boyes coming home loaden with Muskets, Pikes, Swords and Skeanes, enough to Arme 7 or 8 ſcore men, and in hope to get more that were drowned in the River. And thus God hath done for us without the help of <hi>Eniskillen,</hi> whom we long waited for to have contributed for their ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply and reliefe, and all theſe men that were found kil'd, within Musket ſhot of our Caſtle.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letters">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:96993:24"/>
               <head>A copy of ſuch Letters and Papers as were found in the Lieutenant Colonels <hi>Bryan Mac Donnoghy</hi> his Pockets, being killed neare <hi>Mannour Hamilton</hi> Caſtle, on Saturday, <hi>April 1, 1643.</hi>
               </head>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>SIR,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Beleeve you have heard of the great loſſe we have ſuſtained this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning by <hi>Mannour Hamiltons</hi> Souldiers, I pray you to morrow come away your ſelfe and diſpatch proviſion for my Company, who muſt faſt this night; your owne Company is extreame weake here; therefore have all the reſt ſent for ſpeedily, that they may be compleat to morrow to march. This is all for the preſent, I reſt</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>From the Campe at <hi>Crewly,</hi> 
                           <date>
                              <hi>March</hi> 29, 1643.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>Your loving Brother Co: <hi>Lucas Taffe.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>NOble Sir, we are ſtraitly commanded by our Colonell to have all our Company to the full number here this night, and eſpecially he doth deſire your owne ſpeedy repaire hither; and without you ſend for all your men upon ſight hereof, and give them ſtrait charge to be here this night with us, you will otherwiſe be aſhamed for ever, ſeeing we are called upon ſpeedy ſervice: For my owne part, I thought you did regard the loſſe of me more then thus, to leave me here all this while unappoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with Souldiers and Ammunition; for without Gods great helpe, I had never come off alive from the laſt mornings ſervice we had with <hi>Mannour Hamiltons</hi> Souldiers: I pray you as you love your owne cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit and my life, ſend me the reſt of the Souldiers; otherwiſe, if you will let me goe upon ſervice without them, by Chriſt I will never be an Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer under your command more. We have not a pound of Pouder amongſt us all left: Your 8 Musketeeres played their parts moſt gallantly, and diſcharged more ſhot then halfe of the Regiment; but our Pike-men plaid the jade with us. <hi>Hugh ô Hara</hi> is ſhot in the Foote, and 40 more of our Regiment wounded, 2 only killed, none of them yours: This is the hurt we received yeſterday morning; ſo leaving all to your beſt care and diſcretion, I reſt</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>From the Campe of <hi>Crewly,</hi> 
                           <date>the 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of <hi>March.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>Your obedient Lieutenant <hi>Cormack Mac Donnogh,</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:96993:25"/>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>SIR,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Shall deſire that you march towards the falling in of night, with all the Companies on this ſide of the water, where I ſhall meete you: you are to leave one Pike-man out of every Company, to guard the Baggage left at <hi>Crewly,</hi> who you are to require to keepe good watch upon ſuch things as ſhall be left with them, and not to ſpoile any thing belonging to the Abby, as they ſhall anſwer it at their perils; ſo till meeting I reſt</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Yours Co: <hi>Lucas Taffe.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Drumahere,</hi> 
                           <date>March 31.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Belliſedera</hi> the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of <hi>March,</hi> 1642.</head>
                     <p>WHereas feverall grievous complaints are daily exhibited unto us, that the under-named perſons doe daily commit ſeverall incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, maſſacres, robberies, outrages and many other enormities and pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages within the County of <hi>Sligo,</hi> contrary to his Majeſties Lawes, the ſeverall acts of the ſupreame Provinciall and County Counſell to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary provided and enacted; Theſe are therefore in his Majeſties name, to will and require you Lieutenant Colonell <hi>Bryan Mac Connagh</hi> and Serjeant Major <hi>Teig Reagh ô Dowda,</hi> to attach the bodies of the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named perſons, and to that purpoſe, to command ſuch of the Forces of the County of <hi>Sligo</hi> as they ſhall thinke fit; wherein all the Captaines, Officers and private Souldiers of the Forces of the ſaid County, are here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by required and authorized; ſuch of them as ſhall be hereto required, to be aiding and aſſiſting unto theſe, Lieutenant Colonell and Serjeant Major <hi>Teig Reagh ô Dowda,</hi> as they ſhall receive directions; and in caſe that the under-named perſons ſhall not willingly ſuffer themſelves to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended; then the ſaid Lieutenant Colonell and Serjeant Major are to deale with them like common enemies, as well by death as otherwiſe; And theſe Lieutenant Colonell and Serjeant Major <hi>Teig Reagh ô Dowda,</hi> are likewiſe requited to commit the bodies of the under-named perſons, being ſo attached, unto the Caſtle of <hi>Ballynefada,</hi> and there to leave them in ſafe cuſtody, untill they receive further directions from us: And the Captaines, Warriours and aſſiſting to the ſaid Lieutenant Colonell and Serjeant Major <hi>Teig Reagh ô Dowda</hi> in the execution of the premiſes as
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:96993:25"/>they ſhall receive directions, whereof you and every of you may not faile at your extreate perils, <hi>Dat' Anno ſuperiore dicto.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <list>
                              <item>Capt: <hi>Charles ô Connour,</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>Capt: <hi>Hugh ô Connour</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Owen Mac Roe ô Connour,</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Redagh Mac Beryan ô Hart,</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Donnell Mac Rory ô Connor,</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Owen ô Connour,</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Cahill duff Mac Teigh,</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Boy ô Connour,</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Shane ô Hart,</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Teig ô Hart,</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Rore ô Hort,</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Gilpatrick ô Hart,</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Robe ô Binningham,</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Teig ô Connour Sligo,</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Farrall ô Gara,</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Nony ô Hara,</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Andrew Crean,</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>Phelemy ô Connour.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>SIR,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>YOu may perceive by the Lieutenant Generalls Letter, how I am com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to waite in theſe parts, God knowes how long; but no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then after I know the diſtribution of this Army; If greater occaſion then now appeares unto us require it not: though loath I was to be a ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in my owne behalfe for my repairing thither. Truely I have done in that particular more then behoved me, therefore the managing of that Regiment untill further directions is left to your care to diſpoſe of, to uſe and imploy them in all manner of defence or offence, as it to you ſhall ſeeme moſt advantagious to his Majeſties ſervice, and the preſervation of the Countrey. I ſhall alſo deſire you to addreſſe your ſelfe to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of the County, as well to participate of ſuch occurrants as I tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto them, as alſo to forward the execution of ſome particulers concerning the maintenance of your Forces, and the ſpeedy levying there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, imploying in your abſence Serjeant Major <hi>Dowda</hi> to over-ſee and command the Regiment, and to expedite all Country affaires: I hold it requiſite that one well armed Captaine ſhould alwayes reſide within the County. I pray Sir advertiſe me by the bearer, how or in what reſtraint, <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver ô Hara</hi> was kept by the Sheriffe ſince my coming away, It did expect that by this he would cry <hi>mea Culpa:</hi> but ſeeing he ſtands ſo ſtifly upon his juſtification, I promiſe him that I ſhall deſire Juſtice againſt him, as alſo againſt the Sheriffe, if he have not gone according to his dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. I pray cauſe Serjeant Major <hi>Dowda</hi> to be paid for his Pouder, according to my promiſe unto him, and let me heare at large from you, whether any man offers diſobedience amongſt you, that we might take courſe with them: I hope you will not forget to rid poore <hi>Carberry</hi> of the inſolent power of the Northerne, in which caſe I pray you be advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:96993:26"/>by your County Counſell: The encloſed of the Lord of <hi>Elphin,</hi> I pray you endeavour if your occaſion will admit you the leaſure to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh his deſires therein; This being all for the preſent, I am</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your faithfull Brother <hi>Lucas Taffe.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>Tuam</hi> 
                           <date>the 26<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of <hi>Feb:</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>For my worthy Friend <hi>Mulmurry Mac Ternan</hi> Eſquire, Found in his Pocket being kil'd and ſtript.</head>
               <p>KInd Goſſip, the only thing that keepes me from you, is the report that Sir <hi>Frederick Hamilton</hi> promiſed to come laſt night, or this day to ſee me at this Caſtle, which report hath made me and all mine to watch all night: I pray you have a care if you heare any ſuch thing, to march hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with all poſt-haſt with your Company; And ſo I bid you farewell, and reſt</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Dromahere</hi> Caſtle, <date>
                        <hi>Feb.</hi> 21, 1641.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Your owne faithfull Goſſip <hi>Owen ô Rourke.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A Copy of ſuch Letters as were ſent by the Rebels to our Colonel and to his Lady, thinking to have terrified her; and a Copy of other Papers and Writings found in the Pockets of their Prieſts, Friers and Captaines, being killed and ſtript.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Madam,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Am ſory it was never my fortune to be acquainted with your Ladiſhip, though much deſired: Now out of the reſpects I beare unto your Ladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips family, I cannot but be grieved to thinke on the trouble that is like ſoone to fall on you. We have here 23 Companies that are now ready to march towards you, and 15 Companies more upon their much from the uppermoſt part of this County, and the County of <hi>Maio.</hi> I have for your Ladiſhips ſake intreated the Captaines of the Army to write unto Sir <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick,</hi> I ſhould be right glad that he would imbrace the conditions ſent him, for there are many reſolved to looſe all their lives, or they will have Sir <hi>Fredericks</hi> head, notwithſtanding their friends he hath priſoners. For the Army doth proteſt and ſweare, they will have Sir <hi>Frederick</hi> and <hi>Mannour Hamilton</hi> Caſtle, though it coſt the lives of thouſands, and the lives of his Priſoners, rather then to ſuffer him longer to remaine within their boſomes, eſpecially carrying himſelfe as he hath done towards them, It is but in vaine to ſtrive againſt the ſtraeme.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:96993:26"/>If I had not been well aſſured that the Army now in Armes and ready to march, are too ſtrong againſt any powers this Kingdome can make, or rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily come to helpe you, and that which incourageth us moſt to take Armes, is the Juſtneſſe of our cauſe, which is for the maintenance of his Majeſties Prerogatives, our Liberties and Religion, which is ſo much trod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den under-foote, that moſt of all this Kingdome are reſolved to ſacrifice their lives in defence thereof; And if we get not our demands of Sir <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick,</hi> take it on my word he will ſoone repent it: I ſhould be very ſorry that any hurt ſhould come to your Ladiſhip. I make no doubt but you know how neere a kinne, which you will by the bearer, if you doe not, however I will remaine</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>From our Campe at <hi>Sligo.</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>December</hi> 13, 1641.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Your loving Coſen and ſervant <hi>Patrick Flunkett.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>This Paper was found in <hi>Mulmurry Mac Tervans</hi> Pocket.</head>
               <p>WE have agreed, that a ſupply of 200 Souldiers ſhall be preſently preſt and taken up in the Barrony of <hi>Dromahere,</hi> for the ſervice now in hand againſt <hi>Mannor Hamilton</hi> Caſtle, according to the diviſion hereafter expreſſed, witneſſe our hands, this laſt of <hi>January.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Owen O Rowrke.</signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>THe two ſepts of <hi>Chlamloghins</hi> and <hi>Clanmurrayes</hi> are to maintain fou c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore ſouldiers, <hi>Monuterkenny</hi> and <hi>Ballymackenagh</hi> thirty ſouldiers, <hi>Killargy</hi> and <hi>Killimurry</hi> are to maintain fifty ſouldiers, <hi>Leeland</hi> and the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh of <hi>Dromlaſſe</hi> are to maintain fourty ſouldiers.</p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>This Paper was found in a Prieſts pocket, being killed and ſtript.</head>
               <p>WHereas we are certified that the unexpected inſurrection did ariſe in defence of our good faith, and holy Mother, the Catholick <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> Church, and of his Majeſties prerogative Royall, both which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lately intended by the Proteſtants of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> to be abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment wherefore I <hi>Teig O Connour Sligo,</hi> Collonell of the <hi>Jriſh</hi> Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the county of <hi>Sligo,</hi> doe hereby command all the inhabitants of the pariſh of <hi>Cadbry,</hi> as you are naturally obliged to obey the <hi>Romane</hi> Chuch, to pay or cauſe to be payed unto father <hi>Connor O Hary</hi> Paſtour of the ſaid pariſh, all ſuch tithes and other duties as he can ſind out were unpayed to the former Miniſter of the ſaid pariſh, and in failing hereof I promiſe to aſſiſt him as I beſt can, as witneſſe my hand this 17 of <hi>January.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:96993:27"/>
               <p>NOble Sir <hi>Frederick Hamilton,</hi> I cannot forget that in times paſt there was a mutual correſpondency of love, and affectionate friendſhip between my father, and your ſelf, which on your part hath been approved by ſeverall of your favourable courteſies, which hath left ſuch an obligation upon me his ſonne and heire, as I cannot but wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h your happineſſe before your hurt. Though the generall matter now in hand requires the contrary. I am preſwaded you cannot but know or imagine, as true it is, that there is ſo faſt an union made and concluded a mongſt us all the <hi>Romane</hi> Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, as members of one body, we have vowed to help one another, ſo that if one member receiveth hurt, the other muſt apply his beſt endevours for the cure, all tending to the defence of our Chriſtian Religion, and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of his Majeſties moſt Royall power &amp; prerogatives, being the chief reaſons of this our moſt Chriſtian quarrell: Therefore, when I ſaw the moſt miſerable diſtractions &amp; afflictions which my moſt neare Couſins, and Neighbours of this county ſuffered under this pretence by your cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and meanes, my heart could not for the brotherly Chriſtian charity I own unto them, beſides the ſeverall invitations and perſwaſions of many of my friends and alliance, but make this preſent expedition. I have here with me lying about me, beſides a many more drawing towards you for the places to ſeek redreſſe and revenge of theſe great miſeries and calamities you have put upon them, which I wiſh to have in the gentleſt ſort I may. Wherefore, I thought fit to acquaint you more for your own good, then any end of mine, That I am here ſtrong enough from the county of <hi>Sligo,</hi> having all the beſt, and chiefeſt men of that county about me, beſides the ſtrength of the county of <hi>Leytrim</hi> under the command of my Couſins, the <hi>O Rourkes</hi> whom you have much harmed, who have procured by their friends from the county of <hi>Maio</hi> theſe gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t ſupplies, daily drawing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us, ſo that you will find it impoſſible for you to reſiſt, wherefore out of my unfeigned good will do adviſe you that before we go to extremity, you will take the beſt courſe for your own ſafety and relief, which great Potentates and Nobles are not aſhamed to doe, when they are in the like extremities as we hold you to be, in deſiring that you and we may agree upon quatters &amp; a Ceſſation of Arms, untill Articles propounded upon ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide may be agreed upon, I deſire to be free from giving way to ſhed your bloud, if otherwiſe I may compaſſe my pretences: If you will not make uſe of this friendly offer inſtantly without delay, and before the county of <hi>Maio</hi> Gentlemen joyn with me, I feare they being ſo near and great in numbers; I ſhall hardly ſtay their hands from ſee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>king revenge for killing and hanging ſo many of their kinſmen, the <hi>O Rourkes,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of their friends of this County, whom you have deſtroyed, herein I
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:96993:27"/>will expect your preſent anſwer, and deſire that our meſſengers on both ſides may freel paſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> without harm or danger, as is uſuall in all leaguers, Meane time I ſhall remain</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>From our Camp near <hi>Mannor Hamilton,</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>March</hi> the 15 1641</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Yours at pleaſure and hearts deſire <hi>Teig O Connour Sligo</hi> Collonell.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>This Letter anſwered thus.</head>
               <p>YOur loyalty to your King, your faith to your friends once broke, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more to be truſted by me, but revenged as God ſhall enable the hands of him who was loving to your loyall Predeceſſours, whoſe curſe will contribute to your deſtruction, for extingiſhing the memory of their loyalties, Thus I reſt with contempt and ſcorn to all your baſe bragges.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your ſcourge if I can. <hi>F. H.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letters">
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>For <hi>Captain John O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>crean,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>March</hi> 1 1641.</note> Allowed to himſelf and company nineteen quarters of Land, in the pariſh of Collroy.</head>
                     <p>BY the conſent of the Collonell <hi>Teig O Connour Sligo,</hi> who appointed us to allot unto every Captain of his Regimont, that are now encamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about <hi>Mannor Hamilton,</hi> and to ſtop the incurſions of that Garriſon we hold and think fit, that every Captain to this purpoſe ſhall levy, and take up in every quarter of Land that is allowed for his ſhare fourty nine quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of meale unpreſt, and twelve pence of money every week, for the relief of their companies, and for ſo doing this ſhall be their ſufficient warrant, as witneſſe our hands, the day and y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>are above written.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>Andrew Crean, Teig boy O Connour Connor O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ge O hart</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Theſe laſt two killed, and theſe Papers found as they were ſtript.</p>
               <p>We did beat them from their Camp finding this Paper in one of their dead mens pockets.<note place="margin">April <hi>1</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>VVHereas there hath ſeverall-warrants iſſued for the levying of thre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore quarters of meal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, in every quarter of land of a third levy,<note place="margin">Comita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap> Sligo.</note> which three ſeverall l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>vies is within the Barronny of <hi>Carbery,</hi> for the maintaining of the ſouldiers out of the ſaid Barronny now encamped about <hi>Mannor Hamilton,</hi> out of which every ſouldier is to have for his meanes
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:96993:28"/>whilſt he is there fourteen quarts in meale, and twelve pence in money for every week and more. And in as much as we find that there is meale already allotted as is well able to maintain the ſaid Army till the 15 of <hi>May</hi> next. We doe therefore hereby require all Captaines, Collectours to ſurceaſe and keep their hands from collecting any more meale or money then what was allotted in every quarter for the ſaid three levies, whereof the ſeverall Collectours and Captains according to a former warrant, are to meet by a day to give up an exact account thereof. Dated at <hi>Sligo,</hi> the 4 of <hi>April,</hi> 1642.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <hi>Teig O Connor Sligo, Andrew Crean</hi> Captain <hi>Conn O C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nnor</hi> ſince hanged there.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>For the Lieutenant Collonell <hi>Brian</hi> Mr. <hi>Donnogh</hi>
                     </head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>SIR,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I Hope you have taken courſe in my abſence to keep ſome of your forces in action here, leaſt tergiverſation being ill conſtruct by the gentry of this County, not onely having deprived them of your own aid, but ſuch aſſiſtance as they expected from <hi>Maio,</hi> or thus delaying will produce no better effect then ruine and deſtruction, being now nearer unto it, then ever it hath been formerly. The County of <hi>Galway</hi> Gentlemen have of late petitioned to the Earl of <hi>Clanrickard</hi> againſt the Lord <hi>Forbus,</hi> who hath already committed ſeverall acts of hoſtility, that his Lordſhip might perſwade him to part quietly with his forces, or to give them leave to ſtand for their own defence, the anſwer of which was transferred to this day at <hi>Longreagh,</hi> where <hi>Clanrickard</hi> my Lord Preſident, and the chief of that county meet, and from thence my Lord Preſident goeth to <hi>Galloway.</hi> Sir, what their reſolution will be I cannot yet imagine, but feare much ſo generall a meeting will produce a ſtrange iſſue tending to our deſerved ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, which I commit to a higher power to prevent, then any commiſſion that comes from Parliament. The County of <hi>Maio forces</hi> is gathered to <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thruell</hi> and intend to camp upon the confines of that County. My Lord of <hi>Maio</hi> ſent to us for aide, being well known to his Lordſhip how able we are to ſpare any, he was pleaſed to write plainly if we had not in retributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their loſſe ſuſteined in theſe parts parralelled his courteſies, that we ſhould expect no more aid from thence. A fair excuſe, or a fit denyall, ſure the ſmall forces we have here are in greater danger, then that County which needeth, not feare any forraigne invaſion: we are I proteſt unto you not above three hundred in number, not like henceforth to be at any reſt or quietneſſe. The Powder beſtowed upon <hi>Connaught,</hi> is brought partly
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:96993:28"/>to the county of <hi>Maio,</hi> and ſome to the County of <hi>Galloway,</hi> reſolved up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on not to be touched, untill our Provinciall County diſtribute it as they think fitteſt, when the Counſell is held. I cannot well aſſure you, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the arriving of ſhipping at <hi>Sligo</hi> give we no little occaſion of feare which I pray with expedition to certifie me. And if my own repair, be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny whit neceſſary upon the landing any new ſupplies, I will not fail to poſt night and day unto you. I hope your Counſell have agreed to meet often, being very neceſſary, eſpecially now, I doubt not they will be ſoon called upon to meet when ever I receive intelligence of the full &amp; true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions of the county of <hi>Galloway,</hi> I have ſeen late intelligence of <hi>England</hi> of <hi>July</hi> date, concerning the King &amp; Parliament, who are at great diſtance, the Lord of heaven continue them ſo, untill I ſend them an abſolution. The powder made at <hi>Laughlin</hi> is as good as any is in <hi>Ireland,</hi> we ſhall want no more of that commoditie, ſo we be furniſhed with all other neceſſaries. I pray Sir, let my mother uſe all the haſt ſhe can to have the ditch wholly ſcowred about <hi>Ballymote</hi> Caſtle, before the bad weather overtakes it, I pray that I may have every ſecond day what occurrents thoſe parts affoord you. In the intervall I preſent my ſervice to our friends and reſt</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>Caſtle <hi>Keagh</hi> 
                           <date>the 18 of <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>Your loving Collonell <hi>Lucas Taffe.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <hi>This letter was found in a Prieſts pocket that day we kild above</hi> 80 <hi>in the County of Sligo.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="executions" type="list">
               <head>The names of ſuch as have been hanged at Mannor Hamilton by Martiall Law, ſince the beginning of this Rebellion</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <label>Decemb <hi>3.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <list>
                        <item>Turlogh mac Clevor.</item>
                        <item>Neale Mac Cluan.</item>
                        <item>Mann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> O Gallogher</item>
                        <item>Manns O Hoy</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Decem. <hi>12.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <list>
                        <item>Phelomy Duff Mac Cob</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Decemb. <hi>18</hi>
                     </label>
                     <list>
                        <item>Gelpatrick O Kan</item>
                        <item>Brian O Moriice</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Decemb. <hi>20.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <list>
                        <item>Turlogh O Cally.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Ianuary <hi>2.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <list>
                        <item>Brian O Cannan.</item>
                        <item>Con O Rourk <hi>the Collonells brother</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Ianuary <hi>8.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <list>
                        <item>Connour mac. Shane Glaſse</item>
                        <item>Mac Laugblin <hi>the chief of his name.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Aug. <hi>23.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <list>
                        <item>Owen Mac Garraghy.</item>
                        <item>Cormack O Cornan.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Auguſt <hi>31</hi>
                     </label>
                     <list>
                        <item>Shane Mac Skerrie.</item>
                        <item>Iohn Spence.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Septemb. <hi>10.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Captain</hi> Con O Connour.</item>
                        <item>Credough Mac Derno.</item>
                        <item>Cor Mac O Hay <hi>had been a Miniſter.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Teig Mac Goane.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Septemb. <hi>4</hi>
                     </label>
                     <list>
                        <item>Brian Mac Diffet.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Septem. <hi>17.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <list>
                        <item>Donnogh O D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>wde.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Septem. <hi>19</hi>
                     </label>
                     <list>
                        <item>Grany O Dowgan.</item>
                        <item>Patrick O Neale.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Febru. <hi>2</hi>
                     </label>
                     <list>
                        <item>ohn Wytherſpin.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Febru. <hi>11.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <list>
                        <item>Donnogh boy O Bane.</item>
                        <item>Mewe Mac Laughlin.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Feb. <hi>22.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <list>
                        <item>Owen Mac Thomas Murray.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Febru. <hi>26.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <list>
                        <item>Ferrall Mac Kegan.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Mar. <hi>15</hi>
                     </label>
                     <list>
                        <item>Turmultagh Mac Garraghy: Subſheriffe <hi>deputy of</hi> Donegall.</item>
                        <item>Cormack O Hoyes <hi>wife.</hi>
                           <pb n="56" facs="tcp:96993:29"/>
                           <hi>neare kinſwoman to</hi> O Conn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ur.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>8.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <list>
                        <item>Hugh O Hart</item>
                        <item>Donnell O Hart.</item>
                        <item>Grany ny K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>we.</item>
                        <item>Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>lomy mack A Naw</item>
                        <item>Gilpattrick O Mullane</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</label>
                     <list>
                        <item>Laughlin O Degannian</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</label>
                     <list>
                        <item>Call boy mac Garty.</item>
                        <item>Donnogh O Hart</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</label>
                     <list>
                        <item>Hugh O Flin.</item>
                        <item>Iames Roch <hi>the chief Murcherer, of the</hi> Britiſh <hi>at</hi> Sligo.</item>
                        <item>Donnell O Clery.</item>
                        <item>Hugh O Cullen.</item>
                        <item>Glany O Regan.</item>
                        <item>Iames Wytherſpin.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Iuly <hi>12</hi>
                     </label>
                     <list>
                        <item>Iames halfpenny.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Iuly <hi>26</hi>
                     </label>
                     <list>
                        <item>Hugh O Fey</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Novem. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <list>
                        <item>Garrat mac A Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>chief of his name.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Nov. <hi>14.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <list>
                        <item>Cap. Charles mac Gwire</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Nov. <hi>16.</hi>
                     </label>
                     <list>
                        <item>Phelomy Mac Pierce.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Decem. <hi>22</hi>
                     </label>
                     <list>
                        <item>in Gwyre.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Ianuary <hi>7</hi>
                     </label>
                     <list>
                        <item>Edmond Mac Gawran.</item>
                        <item>Turlogh Reagh O Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telan.</item>
                        <item>Brian O Cuer.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>February <hi>3</hi>
                     </label>
                     <list>
                        <item>Cormack O Cuer.</item>
                        <item>Cormack O Quillan.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Februar <hi>18</hi>
                     </label>
                     <list>
                        <item>Ka<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ill mack Kan.</item>
                        <item>Donnel mac Glannag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>y,</item>
                        <item>William mac Roregan.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Sir Robert Hannay his Letter and others being Priſoners at Sligo and ſent to Domahere Caſtle.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Honourable Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>VVE the undernamed perſons having ſuffered in all our whole eſtates and being upon our baniſhment out of this Kingdome, under the ſafe conduct of Mr. <hi>Edmond Bourk Ragagh,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Walter Bourk</hi> of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dagh</hi> towards the North, but moſt oppoſed at Caſtle <hi>Connour Enniſcromne Eſcagh</hi> bridge, <hi>Dawne Neale, Arnagleſſe</hi> and <hi>Tomler</hi> go by ſeverall bands of armed m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n purpoſely ſet for our lives, were not their extream violence ſuppreſſed by the diſcretion, worth and care of thoſe two Gentlemen, and we taken priſoners by the <hi>mac Swines,</hi> brought before <hi>O Connour Sligo,</hi> where we now remain, and intended to be ſent unto the Caſtle of <hi>Dro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maheere</hi> to be kept untill you Sir deliver ſuch priſoners of the <hi>O Rourkes,</hi> and others as you have in your cuſtodie, or to be dealt with, as you doe unto them, Sir, you are nobly diſpoſed, ſo that in honour we hope the meanes of relief, being now in your ſelf, you will not ſuffer us to periſh, who will ever remain, Sir,</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours truly obliged to ſerve you <hi>Robert Hannay, Andrew Adare, Alexander Montgomery. William Liſton, Thomas Fullerton.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>THeſe be the names and number of Priſoners, Sir <hi>Robert Hannay,</hi> his Lady, his two daughters, two boyes, two men, and a Gentlewoman
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:96993:29"/>Mr. <hi>Andrew Adare,</hi> and his wife and ſiſters ſonne, Mr. <hi>Alexander Mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gomery</hi> his wife and eldeſt ſonne, Mr. <hi>William Liston</hi> his wife and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Mr. <hi>Thomas Fullerton</hi> and his wife, <hi>Patrick Deomond,</hi> Mr. <hi>Adares</hi> man.</p>
                  <p>Sir after the writing of this Letter we are brought to <hi>Dromaherre,</hi> and order left by the Captaines to bring us unto the Camp at <hi>Mannor Hamilton,</hi> where we muſt ſuffer death, if thoſe Priſoners with you Sir, be not deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered.</p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Sir Fredrick Hamiltons anſwer to the Letter afore-mentioned.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Have received your Letter, whereby I am given to underſtand of your treacherous ſurpriſall, notwithſtanding of your ſafe conduct promiſed, for the which I am very ſorry, but ſuch is the treacherous falſhood of thoſe diſloyall tray tours generlly throughout this whole Kingdome, that hath made me vow and ſweare in the preſence of Almighty God, that I will never give nor take quarter with them, or any of them, yea though my own ſons who have deſcended from my own Loins, were in your eſtate, I had rather they ſhould die gloriouſly for the cauſe of Chriſt, then I ſhould ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſe my ſelf as to deal with ſuch traitours to God and his Majeſty. Thus beſeeching God Almighty to ſtrengthen and encourage you, that you may continue conſtant till it ſhall pleaſe God to give you deliverance either by life or death. In the meane time I am perſwaded that they will uſe you with no worſe meaſure, then their Priſoners, who were apprehended by me in the action of Rebellion are uſed: So recommending you to God, I reſt,</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Caſtle <hi>Hamilton</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>January</hi> 19. 1641.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Your very loving friend <hi>F. H.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>By Letters from <hi>Dublin</hi> dated <hi>26</hi> of <hi>July</hi> and <hi>2</hi> of <hi>Auguſt</hi> from a good hand.</head>
               <p>THe Lord Marqueſſe of <hi>Ormond</hi> as I heare, hath now writ to the State here, to ſend him Bread and Cheeſe for 5000 men, for that he hath no victualls for his Army, and yet we hoped here, that thoſe Countries would have afforded plenty of victuals, and theſe ſending ſtill abroad, we being in ſuch want at home, makes our neceſſities deſperate. There came lately to Towne here, Lieutenant Colonell <hi>Sentleger,</hi> ſonne unto the late Preſident of <hi>Munſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er,</hi> who came through <hi>Kilkenny,</hi> having a paſſe
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:96993:30"/>for his ſafety from the Viſcount <hi>Muskerry;</hi> he ſaith that at <hi>Kilkenny</hi> he ſaw and dined with the Popes Nuntio who is come thither, and hath brought to the Rebels 80000<hi rend="sup">lb</hi>. This is likewiſe reported by others, who ſay they ſaw him there; and it is much belceved here, <hi>Sentlegers</hi> buſineſſe hether as I heare was about the Ceſſation, to know by what authority it is to be done, and how farre procceeded in; what will be the iſſue of tha bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe is not yet knowne.</p>
               <p>Our Ammunition here growes very ſcarce, and if we be not ſuddainely relieved from <hi>England,</hi> it will be an unanſwerable reaſon for a Ceſſation; and then we muſt either ſubmit to the mercileſſe mercies of theſe cruell Rebels, and to their treachery, or elſe come for <hi>England,</hi> and indure thoſe miſeries and afflictions there which God ſhall pleaſe to lay upon us.</p>
               <p>Romember this, that that pretious thing time; if it be over-paſt but a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before reliefe comes to us, the Kingdome is not like to continue in his Majeſties lgovernement as it now is, but as the Rebels will pleaſe to have it: we now heare that <hi>Preſton</hi> hath diſperſed his Army, and lodged his Ordinance at Sir <hi>Luke fitz Geralds</hi> at <hi>Tecrohon</hi> in <hi>Meath,</hi> that he wants Carriages and Ammunition, ſo that if we could proſecute this Warre, and had proviſions before <hi>Preſton</hi> had againe furniſhed himſelfe, there would be good hopes of putting a ſpeedy end to this Warre, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe will prove long, tedious, and of exceſſive charge, and weary out all the <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We now begin to deſpaire of any help from the Parliament, hearing how unable the Parliament is to ſend any, and that his Majeſty ſo farre proſpers, that we are in hope to have help only from him. We are now like a Candle burnt out, and the ſnuffe in the ſocket giving a little light ſome times, but ready every moment to periſh for want of a new ſupply of oyle.</p>
               <p>Upon Sunday morning about one of the clock, there was a great Alarum here in <hi>Dublin,</hi> the Rebels had got into New-ſtreete, and came up as farre as the pottle, and had pillaged divers houſes before we could make reſiſtance, and ſet ſome thatch houſes on fire, ſome 20 one and other, the certainty is not ſo well knowne though we dwell here, as I can aſſure you of it: the Rebels were as ſome fay who ſaw them 300 Horſe, a great Company of Foote, but how many we know not, (God be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) they were beaten out, and about 20 of them killed, and ſome 6 or 7 of ours, they preſently after burnt a great deale of Hay made up in Cocks about <hi>Ragarr</hi> and <hi>Raſarnam,</hi> and a night or two after about <hi>Donna brooke,</hi> our Army being abroad we could not follow them, but thought our ſelves well that the City was kept fafe, being much afraid of and ſuſpitious the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:96993:30"/>Papiſts within us, though I cannot heare of any proofe againſt any in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular.</p>
               <p>The victualls which were brought us by <hi>Bartlet,</hi> are long ſithence ſpent, and we are now againe in as ill caſe for want as ever, our Army be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the greateſt that ever we ſent out ſince this rebellion; they went neere <hi>Edenderry</hi> which was given up to us, but all pillaged, and the <hi>Crohan</hi> which likewiſe they had taken, they left and burnt it, ſince which time our Army without doing any thing more, came back to <hi>Killcock,</hi> where they have ſince been for ſome dayes paſt in great neceſſities, and very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of our Souldiers dying in the Fields for hunger, ſo that we feare it will conſume in a ſhort time to a ſmall number, though in theſe neceſſitous times we account them as though their numbers were full: The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe came the laſt Thurſday from them to <hi>Dublin,</hi> and yeſterday went back to them againe; and as it is ſaid here, the Army for a great part of them ſhall be placed in out Gariſons, and the reſt come to <hi>Dublin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brent</hi> is come over againe with ſome Letters out of <hi>England,</hi> which were as I heare delivered yeſterday, the Vicetreaſurer, and Sir <hi>John Temple,</hi> and Sir <hi>Robert Meridith</hi> were committed to the Caſtle, and the Maſter of the Wards as I heare, ſhould alſo have bin ſo committed but that he is ſick, and ſo his committall reſpited till he recover his health. So I reſt</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your very loving Friend <hi>S. M.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To my worthy Friend <hi>William Lenthall</hi> Eſquire, Speaker of the Honourable Houſe of Commons in <hi>England,</hi> to be ſpeedily communicated to the Houſe.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Maſter Speaker,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THere is now ſome ſhort time eſſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed ſithence here began a great ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour to be ſpread amongſt us (and much fomented in the mouthes and ears of all ſorts of people) of a treaty for a Ceſſation of Armes to be concluded on betwixt the forces ſetled in and about Dublin, and the Lyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Rebels, and that the ſame was agitated and ſet on foot by vertue and force of ſeverall Letters from his Majeſtie to the Marqueſſe of <hi>Ormond,</hi> and that the buſineſſe hath been in a great probability to take effect untill of late ſome appearance of a breach hath fallen out betwixt them; what the ſubſtance or ſucceſſe of that treaty may be, we in theſe parts have been kept utterly ignorant, and ſo far from being (to our knowledge) compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended therein, or concluded thereby, as that we have not had the leaſt notice thereof, but by the hands of the Rebels, to whom in that, or any
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:96993:31"/>other particular, we have little reaſon to give credit, ſave that at a late parley, which was held betwixt me and the principall Officers of this Army, and the Lord of <hi>Muskery</hi> (who pretended to communicate unto us matter tending to the publique good;) we made ſuch advantage there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as to obtain leave to ſend a Gentleman of our own to the place, where this treaty was related to be in agitation, who ſuddenly returned unto us, with aſſurance that upon ſundry ſpecious overtures made by the Rebels ſuch a Treaty had been entred into, but that the ſame by the appearance of their deluſive irreality was broken off at preſent, and that the Marqueſſe of <hi>Ormond</hi> was then marched into the field with a good ſtrength to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute the Lynſter Rebels. And as we are of opinion that extreme neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity did compell thoſe of the Lynſter Army to harken to ſuch a Treaty, ſo we cannot but avouch our owne wants and generall diſtreſſes to be equall to, if not ſurpaſſing, the ſuffrings of any other part of the Kingdome, And indeed albeit we are moſt faithfully zealous and deſirous to beſtow our lives and fortunes on this cauſe and ſervice; yet will our generall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects and neceſſities diſable us to adminiſter any advantage unto it, being altogether unfurniſhed of ſuch meanes, as might make our perſons and endeavours availeable, or conſiderable: And although we have lately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a ſhip laden with Proviſions, furniſhed out by the care and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of that Honourable Houſe (for which we are deſirous that you would returne them our humble and thankfull acknowledgement of their great favour therein:) yet when the ſame fell out to be divided amongſt out whole Army, it amounted not to above ten dayes proviſion for the common ſouldiers, ſo as I am again inforced to lay the ſouldiers upon the wretched inhabitants of our ſeverall Garriſons, who were altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to ſind either themſelves or the ſouldiers a ſubſiſtance, if ſome private Merchants had not been endueed to bring in proviſions upon their own account; which were ſold out to the poor people, and may make them ſubſiſt untill the harveſt draw on upon us, that we may expect to gain ſomething abroad, which then nevertheleſſe we cannot hope to doe, or to be able to look out of our Garriſons, for the eſpeciall want of powder and Munition, which is ſuch as that our whole ſtores will be utterly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted, and ſpent in meer watching without other ſervice, in one moneth or ſix weeks, having not for all our Garriſons and men above thirty Barrels of Powder, and Match in no ſort proportionable to it; So that I ſhall humbly deſire that in the firſt place we may receive at the leaſt 200 Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels of Powder with Match and lead proportionable, if any ſervice be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected at our hands.</p>
               <p>In the next place, there is caſt upon me a moſt heavie and inſupportable
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:96993:31"/>burthen of ſatisfying and giving contentment to the Officers, who having now neither money or Cloathes (meat being as ſcarce and dainty with them as either) doe daily importune me for leave to forſake the ſervice, which I could not refuſe to ſome few whom I had no meanes to relieve, nor can, but with reluctancy, deny unto the reſt, ſeeing the contemptible and wretched condition they live in, beneath the qualitie of Gentlemen, or indeed common ſouldiers in other parts, and therefore I am enforced to deale with them by perſwaſions, wherein I have hitherto proved ſo ſucceſſefull, and have found them ſo faithfully devoted to this ſervice, as that they are content at my entreaty to wait for, and expect the order and direction of that Honourable Aſſembly, how they ſhall be diſpoſed of, or provided for: And hereupon have I prevailed with the Admirall (whom we are all exceedingly obliged to, for his care and willingneſſe to advance this ſervice) to employ this Pinnace expreſſely with this diſpatch to be communicated unto the Houſe. And ſhall earneſtly beſeech you, as you tender the good and preſervation of this conſiderable and important Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince and Army, that you would effectually repreſent the ſubſtance of this my Letter unto that Honourable Aſſembly, and obtaine and returne unto me ſuch full and ample directions and advertiſements, what ſupply we are to expect, or depend upon, or what other courſe we ſhall apply our ſelves unto, as that we may (according to our generall deſire) ſo diſpoſe of our ſelves as may beſt ſuit with the liking and approbation of that Aſſembly, being confident that they will only Order and Command us ſuch things as may be fezible, at leaſt poſſible for us to obſerve: And now that we may not in the <hi>interim</hi> periſh before any ſupplies or directions can overtake us, or returne unto us, (which we ſhall be in great danger of) if we receive not a ſudden reſolution. I ſhall make humble ſuit that this Pinnace may be diſpatched back with all poſſible ſpeed. And ſeeing we have already re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived good benefit by the Aſſiſtance of the Admirall; I ſhall alſo humbly deſire that a courſe may be conceived to continue him upon this Coaſt, and that he may be directed to comply with me in all occaſions of ſervice, for that it is very probable we may by his help, when we ſhall have ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes, take in divers of the ſea Towns, which had been performed ere this time, if ever we had been in a condition (ſince his coming to us) fit to March into the field. The enemie advancing lately to the ſiege of <hi>Capper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin</hi> and <hi>Lyſmore,</hi> which places (in regard I was unable to draw forth the whole Army, through meere want of all kind of neceſſaries) I did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devour to ſtreng then with men, and proviſions, and to that purpoſe mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with a good party of foot, and ſome horſe to <hi>Tallow</hi> within two miles of their Campe, and there lay to face them, and attempt the putting
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:96993:32"/>in of proviſions into the ſaid ſeverall places: I had there an opportunity to have a perfect view of their whole Forces, and did finde as well by my eſpyals, as by my particular ſurvay, that their ſtrength of horſe did at the leaſt treble ours (although ours according to their ſeverall numbers, were indifferently full) and that they were very competently armed, which gave me then occaſion and reſolution to deſire you would repreſent unto that Honourable Aſſembly how that Sir <hi>Iohn Pawlet,</hi> Knight, having by his induſtry and earneſt deſire to advance this ſervice, gotten a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble number of ſerviceable men, well mounted together, who have on all occaſions been employed, and ſhewed themſelves active and able in the performance of ſeverall ſervices, I have for their incouragement and for the keeping of them together, and for the ſtrengthening of our Horſe iſſued ſome ſmall quantity of Tobaccoes unto them, to keep them alive, and promiſed to uſe my endeavours to gaine them an entertainment; I ſhall therefore earneſtly deſire you to repreſent unto the Houſe, that if they will vouchſafe to ſupply Sir <hi>Iohn Pawlet</hi> with a ſmall ſum of money, and ſome Arms to recruite and compleat them (which are the only thing they want) and to give me Order to enter them into pay and entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment under his Command, that there will be a very ſerviceable and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Troope raiſed for the publique ſervice, and ſuch an one as will bring a good addition of ſtrength to this Army. I have formerly of late directed moſt of my diſpatches unto Serjeant Major <hi>Jephſon,</hi> a Member of the Houſe, and an induſtrious ſolicitour for the Province (to avoyd your too much trouble) but now I muſt deſire your favours and furtherance in the returne of this diſpatch, (he being probably come thence) in atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance whereon I remain</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Cork</hi> 
                     <date>7. <hi>Aug.</hi> 1643.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Your affectionate friend and ſervant <hi>INSIQUIN.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:96993:32"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
